<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A defence of the Scriptures, and the Holy Spirit speaking in them, as the chiefe iudge of controversies of faith ... with a vindication of that honour due to magistrates, ministers, and others ... in a relation of a disputation at Chesterfield in the county of Darby, between some ministers of the Gospell and James Naylor, an erring Quaker ... : with some animadversions upon a lying relation of that disputation, published by Iames Nayler / by Immanuel Bourne ...</title>
            <author>Bourne, Immanuel, 1590-1672.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1656</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 146 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 33 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A28899</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing B3852</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R23281</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12495015</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12495015</idno>
            <idno type="VID">62479</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A28899)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 62479)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 307:9)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A defence of the Scriptures, and the Holy Spirit speaking in them, as the chiefe iudge of controversies of faith ... with a vindication of that honour due to magistrates, ministers, and others ... in a relation of a disputation at Chesterfield in the county of Darby, between some ministers of the Gospell and James Naylor, an erring Quaker ... : with some animadversions upon a lying relation of that disputation, published by Iames Nayler / by Immanuel Bourne ...</title>
                  <author>Bourne, Immanuel, 1590-1672.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[10], 54 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for John Wright ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1656.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Union Theological Seminary Library, New York.</note>
                  <note>Marginal notes.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Naylor, James, 1617?-1660.</term>
               <term>Society of Friends --  Controversial literature.</term>
               <term>Holy Spirit --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-12</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-12</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-07</date>
            <label>Geremy Carnes</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-07</date>
            <label>Geremy Carnes</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:62479:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A defence of the Scriptures, and the Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Spirit ſpeaking in them, as the chiefe Iudge of Controverſies of Faith, and of the light in them, as needfull to be looked unto for di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection to attaine Salvation:</p>
            <p>With a Vindication of that Honour due to Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrates, Miniſters, and others, according to their Places and Dignities.</p>
            <p>In a Relation of a Diſputation at <hi>Cheſterfield</hi> in the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of <hi>Darby,</hi> between ſome Miniſters of the Goſpell, and <hi>James Nayler</hi> an erring Quaker.</p>
            <p>The Queſtions diſputed were theſe foure:
<list>
                  <item>1. <hi>Whether the Spirit of God ſpeaking in the Scripture, be the chiefe Judge of Controverſies of Faith?</hi> Affirmed by us Miniſters of Chriſt.</item>
                  <item>2. <hi>Whether the private Spirit in the Pope, or in any Quaker, be the chiefe Judge of Controverſies?</hi> Denyed.</item>
                  <item>3. <hi>Whether every man be bound to looke to the light within him (as ſufficient) for his direction to attaine Salvation?</hi> Denyed.</item>
                  <item>4. <hi>Whether it be lawfull to call any man Maſter or Father, upon earth (or to give any honour to man?)</hi> Affirmed.</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>In which, The Truth is confirmed, and the Quakers Errors and Blaſphemies diſcovered, and confuted, and many places of Scripture from the <hi>Quakers</hi> falſe applica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, cleared, With ſome Animadverſions upon a lying Relation, of that diſputation, pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhed by <hi>Iames Nayler.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>A man that is an Hereticke, after the firſt and ſecond admonition, reject; knowing, that he that is ſuch is ſubverted, and ſinneth, being condemned of himſelfe,
<bibl>Tit. 3.10, 11.</bibl>
            </q>
            <p>By <hi>Immanuel Bourne,</hi> Paſtor of the Church in <hi>Aſhover</hi> in the County of <hi>DARBY.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>London,</hi> Printed for <hi>John Wright</hi> at the <hi>Kings Head</hi> in the <hi>Old Bailey,</hi> 1656.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:62479:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:62479:2"/>
            <head>To the Right Honourable, <hi>Iohn Glyn,</hi> Lord chiefe Juſtice, and to the Honorable
<list>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Richard Aske</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Peter Warbarton</hi>
                  </item>
               </list> Juſtices of the Upper Bench.</head>
            <head>To the Right Honourable, <hi>Oliver Saint Iohn</hi> Lord Chiefe Juſtice, and to the Honorable
<list>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Edward Atkins,</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Matthew Hales,</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Hugh Windham,</hi>
                  </item>
               </list> Juſtices of the Court of Common Pleas.</head>
            <head>To the Right Honorable, <hi>William Steele,</hi> Lord chiefe Baron, and to the Honorable
<list>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Iohn Parker,</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Ro Nicolas,</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>R Tomlins,</hi>
                  </item>
               </list> Barons of His Highneſs Court of Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chequer.</head>
            <head>To the Right Honorable, Commiſſiary Generall <hi>Edward Whaley,</hi> Major Generall of the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties of Nottingham Darby, Lincoln, Leiceſter &amp; Warwick.</head>
            <head>And to all other the Honorable and Worſhipfull Juſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces and Officers, for the preſervation of piety, and the peace of the Nation: The bleſſing of truth and true peace here, &amp; eternal happines hereafter.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Right Honorable,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">M</seg>AY it pleaſe your honours, to give me leave to become your humble remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brancer; That when <hi>Joſhua,</hi> that religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, wiſe, faithfull, and valiant Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine, Generall of all the Armies of Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rael, had conquered one &amp; thirty Kings, and by Gods aſſiſtance, ſetled the Lords people in the promiſed land, to witneſſe his care of piety, as well as of peace, He calleth for all Iſrael, for their Elders, their Heads, their Judges, and for their Officers, and mindeth them of the mighty works the Lord had done for them, and preſſed them upon that account, to ſtir up their af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections,
<pb facs="tcp:62479:3"/>to love the Lord their God, and to feare him and ſerve him in truth and ſincerity; yea, to put away their falſe gods, and falſe worſhip from amongſt them. And we read likewiſe of faithfull <hi>Samuel,</hi> that hee jud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged Iſrael all the daies of his life, and hee went from yeare to yeare in Circuit, to <hi>Bethel,</hi> and <hi>Gilgal,</hi> and <hi>Mizpeh,</hi> and he judged Iſrael in all thoſe places, and his returne was to <hi>Ramah,</hi> for there was his houſe, and there he judged Iſrael, and there he built an Altar unto the Lord Thus here you ſee, there was both Juſtice and Piety in this holy man of God, and Iſrael was bleſſed in ſuch a Judge. We cannot but acknowledge, that the Lord hath done great things in theſe Nations, and wee doe enjoy peace and plenty, and many mercies, which we have not prized nor improved as we ought to the beſt advantage, for Gods glory, and our own good. Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der his Highneſſe protection, and the preſent Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, through the grace of God, every man may ſit quietly under his own vine and fig-tree, without feare of plundering, a happineſs which in few yeares paſt we did not enjoy; Yea, we have good Lawes, and ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nourable religious Judges and Magiſtrates, to ſee Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice executed, and right done between man and man; and wee enjoy our comfortable Liberty of preaching and hearing the Goſpell of Chriſt; Yet can we not ſay, there is no complaining, nor cauſe of complaint in our ſtreets. The Church and people of God have met with enemies in all ages:
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Cant.</hi> 2.2.</note> As is the Lillie amongſt the thorns, ſo is my beloved among the daughters, and as it was of old, ſo it is in theſe our daies; the Church and people of God, eſpecially Gods faithfull Miniſters, ſuffer perſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, by two ſorts of people. The firſt, prophane Ran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, Atheiſticall men, Drunkards, Gameſters, and igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant blind ſoules, ſuch as neglect publike Ordinances in theſe times of liberty, and have no right principle of grace and goodneſs in them: Theſe make it a delight to exerciſe their malice againſt the Miniſters of Chriſt: Theſe would rob and ſpoile them to the uttermoſt, if it
<pb facs="tcp:62479:3" rendition="simple:additions"/>were in their power: And this we can witneſs we have found true by troubleſome experience. Againe, there is another ſort of people, which travell up and downe the Nation, under the name of Quakers, as the Jeſuits and ſeminary Prieſts have uſed to doe ſecretly; ſo theſe now openly diſswading and ſeducing our peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple all they can, from commitig to our Churches, or meeting houſes, calling our Churches, Idols Temples; All our ſervices to God in praier, preaching of the word, and other Chriſtian exerciſes, ordinary, and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traordinary; when wee ſeeke the face of God for the peace and welfare of the Nation, for the proſperity of our Navie and Armies, both by ſea and land, or our prai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing God for his mercies we do enjoy. All theſe (ſay the Quakers) are but Idol-worſhip,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>In a Quakers book called a Diſcovery of a threefold ſtate of Antichriſt by</hi> Samuel Bal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>livant <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </note> and beaſtly ſervi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces; and all the faithfull and godlie Miniſters of Chriſt, without exception, are thieves; our maintenance by Tithes, Antichriſtian, and unlawfull: Yea they call us Conjurers, Antichriſts, witches, devils, liars, a viperous and ſerpentine generation, blaſphemers, ſcarlet coloured beaſts, Babylons Merchants, whited wals, painted Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pulchres; and whatſoever the true Prophets of God, or Chriſt our Saviour did juſtly call the falſe Prophets, wicked prieſts, and Scribes, and Phariſees, thoſe names do theſe rayling and reviling Quakers give to the god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, painfull, learned and faithfull Miniſters of Chriſt in the Nation, diſswading our people from hearing us, or giving heed to any thing we preach, diſturbing us in our publike miniſtrie. And what can we call this but a per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecution, like that of thoſe wicked men againſt the good Prophet <hi>Jeremie;</hi> Come ſay they, and let us ſmi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e him with the tongue, and let us not give heed to any of his words? <hi>Jer.</hi> 18.18. And what is perſecution, if this be not? Yea ſuch is the malice of theſe Jeſuited Quaking adverſaries againſt the miniſters of Chriſt, that we have juſt cauſe to feare, they had ſome deſigne before this day, to have brought to paſs bloody projects to our ruine, had not God our moſt high protector, and his
<pb facs="tcp:62479:4" rendition="simple:additions"/>Highneſs under God, been provident to prevent thoſe common mutinies, and inſurrections, which in all ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pearance, had been plotted againſt this Nation, and the good people thereof, and then we doubt not but our Quaking, and our prophane atheiſticall adverſaries, like <hi>Herod</hi> and <hi>Pontius Pilate</hi> againſt Chriſt, would both have agreed againſt us to our deſtruction, if the Lord our good God ſhould not preſerve us. What conſtructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on elſe can wee make of thoſe bitter threatnings, not only in words and to our faces (one of the Quakers tel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling me,
<note place="margin">Thus I was threatned by E. S. a Quaker ſince dead.</note> that <hi>I</hi> was plundered formerly by the Caval<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liers, but it ſhould not be long, but my houſe ſhould be pulled downe, and <hi>I</hi> thruſt out of doors.) But to the ſame effect alſo in their written papers,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>A deſcription of the true and falſe Temple, page</hi> 45. <hi>Nayler in his falſe relation.</hi>
               </note> and printed pamphlets: Howle ye Prieſts (ſay ſome of them) the Lord is comming to beat up your quarters by his ſword and fire, and great ſhall be the ſlaine of the Lord. And God is riſen to cut you off (ſaith <hi>James Nayler</hi> himſelf.) And the former concludes, alas, alas poor Prieſts, your downfall is near at hand, ſubſcribed, publiſhed by <hi>Tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mas Aldam, Benjamin Nicolſon,</hi> and <hi>John Harwood.</hi> And another of them, the Lord is comming to beat up your quarters, all ye proud Prieſts, and downe with this deceiver, tith-monger and robber, and down with this Idols Temple, as if they would ſtir up the people to pull down our Churches, and to deſtroy all the faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full Miniſters of the Goſpell in the Nation, on a ſudden; and this ſubſcribed as an Oracle from heaven, written from the Spirit of the Lord. <hi>I</hi> let paſs divers others; But <hi>I</hi> humbly conceive in theſe Alarums, it is fit the Miniſters of Chriſt ſhould be awakened, as to be faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full in their places, and to walke believingly, holily, and humbly with God, ſo to ſeek timely for protection and ſafety in the Lord, and to whom under God, ſhould we ſeek, but to that high power and authority, and to thoſe honourable Judges and Magiſtrates, whom the Lord in his moſt wiſe providence, hath raiſed up, and ſet over us, for the puniſhment of evill doers, and for the praiſe
<pb facs="tcp:62479:4"/>of them that doe well; and we acknowledge Gods goodneſſe, that he hath moved the heart of his High<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>His Highneſſe Declaration, November</hi> 21. 1655.</note> to take notice of the abuſe of that Liberty of Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience, as by others, ſo by theſe our adverſaries, who make too bold, thereby to diſturbe and perſecute Gods faithfull Miniſters; yea under pretence of honouring God, to diſhonour and contemne the honourable Jud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges and Magiſtrates in the land, keeping on their hats, when they are called to anſwer before them, and refu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing to give any reſpect or outward ſhew of reverence to them: Yea, ſuch they are, as in their blind zeale, to an imaginary reformation, and conceited or pretended obedience to Chriſt,
<note place="margin">Richard Farn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worth, a Qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ker, in a pam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phlet of his, &amp;c.</note> would perſwade people to caſt away, not only the good and wholſome lawes, but all our learned Lawyers (as well as Divines) be they never ſo pious, honeſt and faithfull (of which bleſſed be God we have many in the land) yet theſe muſt be baniſhed alſo, as unfit (ſay they) for any Chriſtians to make uſe of; and as if all going to law (though upon never ſo juſt grounds) were unlawfull for any that profeſſeth Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtianity, without which, and the aſſiſtance of our ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nourable Judges, and good Magiſtrates, what lawleſſe, wicked lives would a multitude lead? And we that are the faithfull miniſters of Jeſus Chriſt, have cauſe fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to acknowledge Gods goodneſſe, in ſtirring up his Highneſſe (under God) our ſupreme Protector, with his honourable Councill,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>His Highneſſe proclamation, Feb.</hi> 15. 1654.</note> to ſend forth his late Proclama<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, againſt ſuch prophane Ranters and Quakers, to prohibite the diſturbance of us Miniſters and other Chriſtians in our ſolemn aſſemblies. Since which Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clamation (bleſſed be God) wee have had much more quietneſs in our exerciſes of religion, and congregati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, then formerly we had: But yet we are not without malicious enemies, prophane perſons, as ill as Quakers; And therefore to whom under God, and his Highneſs under him, ſhould we apply our ſelves, but to you my honourable Lords, and to all other the honourable. Jud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges Magiſtrates and Officers, who are appointed for the
<pb facs="tcp:62479:5"/>preſervation of the peace and welfare of the Nation; And eſpecially I am bold to apply my ſelfe to you my honoured Lords, in more particular, whoſe great Abili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, Wiſedome, Juſtice, Goodneſs, and Faithfulneſs, which I have obſerved in a ſerious examination of ſuch cauſes, which in your Circuits (and in particular, in ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verall Aſſies at <hi>Darby</hi>) have come before your ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nours for tryall; your judicious diſcerning between things that differ, between right and wrong, between a petty frivolous action, brought by a malicious adver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary, brought only to vex a poor man; your diſcounte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nancing of malice, and that abuſe of the good Lawes; your juſt ſentences given to the honour of God, the good lawes of the land, and to the comfort of poore men oppreſsed. Theſe things have encouraged me to dedicate this my defence of the Scriptures, &amp; vindica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the honour of Magiſtrates, Miniſters, and others according to their place &amp; dignities. Unto your honors, and all that have power and authority in the execution of Juſtice, and preſervation of piety, and the peace of this Common-wealth, humbly ſupplicating the conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuance as of his Highneſs, ſo under him, of all your pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tections, and favourable aſpects upon, and unto all Gods faithfull Miniſters, to maintaine them in that which is their juſt rights, againſt their malicious adverſaries; yea to defend and maintaine the honour of magiſtracy,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rom.</hi> 13.1.</note> as an Ordinance of God, for the comfort and ſafety of his people, and to defend Chriſt, and the truth of the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpell of Jeſus; to defend the honour and glory of the Lord (the moſt high Protector of his Church) againſt all open prophaneſs, and odious hereſies, and abomina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble blaſphemies whatſoever, that it may appeare, we are a people taught by Chriſt, as the truth is in Jeſus, and that the Lord of Hoſts may appeare for us as our Protector to the end, even till <hi>Shilo</hi> come againe. Moſt humbly praying in my daily addreſses to the throne of grace, not only for my ſelfe, but for all my reverend bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren, the godly, faithfull miniſters of the Goſpell of
<pb facs="tcp:62479:5"/>Chriſt, that the Lord will more and more fill our hearts with his ſpirit of grace, wiſedome, holineſs and zeale, that we may in a right way of holineſs,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iude</hi> 3.</note> meekneſs and truth, contend for the faith that was once delivered to the Saints, that our own lives may be as becoms the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpel of peace, that we may win others to walk in peace and holineſs, and by our own good converſation,
<note place="margin">1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.15.</note> put to ſilence the ſcandals of malicious, &amp; the ignorance of fooliſh men, that God wil give repentance, &amp; free par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don in Chriſt to all our Adverſaries, who complain of us as contentious; becauſe (though after long ſufferings) we ſeeke in a juſt and lawfull way to recover our due and juſt Rights, which they unjuſtly detaine from us; deſiring if it be the will of God, that they may obtaine ſalvation in the Lord Jeſus, and be delivered from wrath to come and that one day they may enjoy a hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py and peaceable communion with us in glory, and to conclude, daily powring out my ſoule to God, That the Lord, the great Protector of Sion, will be pleaſed to preſerve his Highneſs and Honourable Councell, and you my Honourable Lords, and the reſt of the Honoura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Judges, Juſtices, Magiſtrates, and other Worthies, who are Actors for Piety and Peace, to Gods glory, and the benefit of theſe Nations, together with this whole Common wealth, in Truth, Unity and Peace, long to continue.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Moſt humbly ſubſcribing my ſelfe, Your Honours daily Oratour at the Throne of Grace, <hi>Immanuel Bourne,</hi> Paſtor of the Church in <hi>Aſhover.</hi>
               </signed>
               <dateline>London, <date>Feb. 26. 1655.</date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:62479:6"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:62479:6"/>
            <head>A Defence of the Scriptures, and of the Holy Spirit of God ſpeaking in them as the chiefe Judge of Controverſies of Faith, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> In a Diſputation at <hi>Cheſterfield</hi> in the County of <hi>Darby, Jan.</hi> 3. 1654.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">F</seg>Irſt, when the Miniſters came to the Church or Meeting Houſe-yard, <hi>Iames Nayler</hi> was there with his company, but ſeemed unwilling to goe into the Church or Church-Houſe, yet at laſt went into the lower end, and ſtood there. But when Mr <hi>Billingsley</hi> Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter of <hi>Cheſterfield,</hi> began with praier to God for a bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing upon the meeting, <hi>Nayler</hi> and his fellowes went forth againe, pretending ſome plot might be againſt them. But after praier, aſſurance given there was none, they came in againe.</p>
            <p>Secondly, Mr <hi>John Billingſley</hi> began to read the Queſtions; But after <hi>Nayler</hi> read them in the Paper ſent to him (as I take it) and then began to read his Anſwer in writing, and when he had read his Anſwer to the firſt Queſtion, it was deſired that that Queſtion,
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:62479:7"/>and his Anſwer to that, might be firſt Argued, and ſo the reſt afterwards in order.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Queſtion. </seg>1</label> The firſt Queſtion was, Whether the Spirit of God ſpeaking in the Scriptures, bee the chiefe Judge of Controverſies of Faith. Mr <hi>Bourne</hi> ſhewed <hi>Nayler</hi> the Bible, and asked him if he would owne that as Gods word, he anſwered, part of it, or to that effect.</p>
            <p>Firſt, For the ſtate of the Queſtion. By the Spirit, was meant the Spirit of God,
<note place="margin">1 <hi>Iohn</hi> 5.7.</note> the third Perſon in Trinity, one with the Father and the Sonne.</p>
            <p>Secondly, by the Scriptures, the Canonicall books of the Old and New Teſtament.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, By the Spirit of God ſpeaking in the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, that voice or ſpeaking forth of Gods Spirit recor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded in Scripture, which is there now to be found; ſo whether the holy Scriptures, or Spirit in them be judg. This ſtate was not ſo fully opened by reaſon of diſtur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bance even in the entrance, <hi>Nayler</hi> endeavouring to avoid this Queſtion.</p>
            <p>
               <label>Naylers Anſwer</label> 
               <hi>Nayler</hi> in his Anſwer, owned the Spirit that did ſpeake in the holy men, who gave forth the holy Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures to be Judge; and ſaid that Spirit was Judge be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Letter was written, and all Controverſies were judged by that Spirit, but hee did not owne that Spirit that doth now ſpeak in the Scriptures: Hee ſaid hee granted the Spirit was Judge, and would have avoided the Queſtion.</p>
            <p>
               <label>Mr Bournes Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply.</label> But Mr <hi>Bourne</hi> preſſed to go on with the Queſtion, and affirmed it was one thing to ſay the Spirit that did ſpeake in the holy men that gave out the Scriptures was Judge, and another to ſay the Spirit of God ſpeak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in the Scriptures, was Judge, or that the holy Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture was Judge. Therefore preſſed to go on with the Queſtion, and began (as I remember) with this Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon.</p>
            <p>
               <label>
                  <hi>Mr Bourns</hi> 1 <hi>Argument.</hi>
               </label> Whatſoever was and is the ſpeaking forth of the Holy Ghoſt himſelfe, that was and is the chiefe Judge
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:62479:7" rendition="simple:additions"/>of Controverſies of Faith, but the holy Scriptures are the ſpeaking forth of the holy Spirit himſelfe, therefore they are the chiefe Judge of Controverſies of Faith. The firſt propoſition was not denied, and the ſecond was proved, <hi>Acts</hi> 1.16. the Scripture which the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Ghoſt by the mouth of <hi>David</hi> ſpake concerning <hi>Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>das.</hi> Here it is evident what Scriptures <hi>David</hi> writ, or ſpake by writing, that the Holy Ghoſt ſpake; Therefore the holy Scripture is the ſpeaking forth of the Holy Ghoſt, and ſo judge of Controverſies. The ſame again witneſſed by the Spirit, <hi>Acts</hi> 28.25. wel ſpake the Holy Ghoſt by the mouth of <hi>Iſaias</hi> the Prophet, ſaying, &amp;c. Here you ſee the Holy Ghoſt is witneſſed (by the Apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi>) to ſpeak by the mouth of <hi>Iſaias;</hi> and that Scripture which <hi>Iſaiah</hi> writ, was the ſpeaking forth of the Holy Ghoſt, and ſo the ſupreme Judge of Contro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſies, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>
               <label>Naylers Anſwer</label> 
               <hi>Nayler</hi> gave no direct anſwer, but he wrangled, and ſaid, he did owne the Spirit to be Judge, but not the written word, or to that effect; and that the Spirit did ſpeak not in the dead, but in the living; which was (as I did underſtand him) not in the dead letter of the Scripture, but in living men, and vapoured as if he had ſaid much, but yet would have avoided the Queſtion, as needleſſe to be further diſputed on, ſince he did yield the Spirit to be Judge, although he denyed that the Spirit ſpeaking in Scripture, was the chiefe Judge of Controverſies of Faith; But Mr <hi>Bourn</hi> went on to preſs another Argument.</p>
            <p>
               <label>
                  <hi>Mr Bourns</hi> 2 <hi>Argument.</hi>
               </label> Whatſoever Chriſt himſelfe did appeale unto, as to a chiefe Judge, and ſend his hearers unto, as to a chiefe Judge of Controverſies of Faith, that is and ought to be eſteem'd the chief Judge of Controverſies of Faith: But Chriſt himſelfe appealed to the Scriptures, and ſent his hearers to the Scriptures, as to the chiefe Judge of Controverſies of Faith, therefore the holy Scriptures are the chiefe Judge of Controverſies of Faith. The firſt not denyed, the ſecond witneſſed by the Spirit in <hi>John</hi>
               <pb n="4" facs="tcp:62479:8" rendition="simple:additions"/>5.39. in that great controverſie of Faith, whether Chriſt were the Sonne of God, or equall with God? Chriſt appeales to the Scriptures, <hi>Search the Scriptures, for in them you thinke to have eternall life, and they are they that teſtifie of me,</hi> therefore the Scriptures are the chiefe Judge.</p>
            <p>
               <label>Naylers Anſwer</label> 
               <hi>Nayler</hi> did not give any anſwer to ſatisfie the Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, but ſaid ſtill, the Spirit was the Judge, not the written word, and cried out, liar, liar, hold thy peace, the Spirit is Judge, not the written word. Mr <hi>Bourne</hi> bad him yield the Queſtion, ſince Chriſt himſelfe appealed to the Scriptures; But he cried out, and one of his fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low Quakers, away lyar, the Spirit is Judge. Mr <hi>Bourn</hi> replied, The Spirit is Judge, but not the Spirit ſpeak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in any man, but the Spirit ſpeaking in the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, and preſſed a third Argument.</p>
            <p>
               <label>
                  <hi>Mr Bourns</hi> 3 <hi>Argument.</hi>
               </label> Whatſoever is the very word of God himſelfe, that is, and ought to be the chiefe Judge of Controverſies of Faith; But the holy Scriptures are the very word of God himſelfe, and therefore they are the chiefe Judge of Controverſies of Faith.</p>
            <p>The firſt not denied, the ſecond proved, <hi>John</hi> 10.34, 35 <hi>Jeſus ſaid, is it not written in your Law, I have ſaid ye are Gods:</hi> If he called them gods to whom the word of God came, and the Scriptures cannot be broken, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Here our Saviour calleth the Scriptures the word of God, therefore the holy Scripture is the word of God. And the like againe, <hi>Marke</hi> 7.12, 13. <hi>Ye make the word of God of none effect by your traditions.</hi> Chriſt plainly calleth the Scriptures the written Law of God, the word of God, therefore the holy Scriptures are the very word of God himſelfe, and ſo the chiefe Judge of Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troverſies of Faith.</p>
            <p>
               <label>Naylers Anſwer</label> 
               <hi>Nayler</hi> cavilled ſtill and cried out it is falſe, it is falſe, the word is not the Judge, and ſit downe liar. But Mr <hi>Bourne</hi> preſſed him to anſwer; And <hi>Nayler</hi> ſaid, the word was God, but the Scripture was the letter, and that was not Judge.</p>
            <pb n="5" facs="tcp:62479:8" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>
               <label>
                  <hi>Mr Billingſleys</hi> 1 <hi>Argument.</hi>
               </label> Mr <hi>Billingſley</hi> preſſed an Argument, to prove that the written word, of which the Queſtion is made, is not God. That which is the word of Chriſt, who is God, that is not Chriſt, nor God; But the holy Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, and word preached, and written by the Apoſtles, is the word of Chriſt; Therefore the holy Scripture is not Chriſt nor God.</p>
            <p>Firſt, that Chriſt is God, that is evident, <hi>Rom.</hi> 9.5. of whom concerning the fleſh Chriſt came, who is God over all, bleſſed for ever. Therefore by this teſtimony it is evident, Chriſt is God.</p>
            <p>Secondly, that the holy Scriptures and word preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by the Apoſtles, is the word of Chriſt, that is wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſed, <hi>Col.</hi> 3.16. <hi>Let the word of Christ dwell in you richly, in all wiſdome.</hi> The Apoſtle doth not ſay, let the word Chriſt dwell in you, but let the word of Chriſt; Therefore the word of Chriſt is not Chriſt nor God, ſo neither the holy Scriptures which are the word of Chriſt, and of the ſpirit of Chriſt, which holy men ſpake and writ, as they were moved by the Holy Ghoſt.</p>
            <p>
               <label>Naylers Anſwer</label> 
               <hi>Nayler</hi> inſtead of a better Anſwer, ſtill quarrelled, and cried out, liar, liar, the word is God, and God and his word are all one, but the letter was in time.</p>
            <p>
               <label>Mr Bourns Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply.</label> To this Mr <hi>Bourne</hi> replyed, that was not ſo; for al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though God and his written word were one in reſpect of that agreement of truth, was in the written word, and in God; yet that word of God and God, were not all one eſſentially, as the naturall word or Son of God, was all one and the ſame Eſſence or Being with God.</p>
            <p>
               <label>Naylers Anſwer</label> To this <hi>Nayler</hi> cried out, away with thy dark word,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iohn</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.12, 14.</note> I do not owne that word eſſentially, and ſo rejected the diſtinction of Gods written word, and eſſentiall word.</p>
            <p>
               <label>Mr Bourns Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply.</label> Mr <hi>Bourne</hi> replied, that the written word of God was not of the ſame Being with God.</p>
            <p>
               <label>Naylers Anſwer</label> 
               <hi>Nayler,</hi> and one of his fellow Quakers by him, cried out, liar, liar, ſtop thy mouth for ſhame, ſtop thy mouth, God and his word are all one.</p>
            <p>
               <label>Mr Bournes Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument.</label> Mr <hi>Bourne</hi> bad <hi>Nayler</hi> hearken to an Argument to
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:62479:9" rendition="simple:additions"/>prove it by Scripture, and told <hi>Nayler</hi> he was the bra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zen fac'd, foule mouth'd fellow he had heard, when his owne mouth was ſtopped, that he could not anſwer an Argument, he ſtill cried out, liar, liar, ſtop thy mouth, ſtop thy mouth.</p>
            <p>
               <label>Mr Bourns Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument.</label> And Mr <hi>Bourne</hi> preſſed this Argument: No word which was written in time, part by God himſelfe, and part by <hi>Moſes,</hi> and other holy men of God, was or is all one with God eſſentially, or of the ſame eſſence or being with God; but the holy Scriptures were written part by God himſelfe in time, and part by <hi>Moſes,</hi> and other holy men of God; Therefore that word of God was not of one or of the ſame Eſſence and Being with God.</p>
            <p>The firſt Propoſition is evident of it ſelfe. The ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond is witneſſed, <hi>Exod.</hi> 31.18. where God gave un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to <hi>Moſes,</hi> when he had made an end of communing with him, two Tables of ſtone written with the finger (or by the power) of God. And <hi>Exod.</hi> 34.27. God com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded <hi>Moſes</hi> to write all the words of the Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant, for after the tenour of theſe words, I have made a Covenant with thee, and with Iſrael (And this was written two thouſand yeare after the Creation of the world which God made) therefore God and that writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten word was not all one, or of the ſame Eſſence and Being with God, and ſo not the reſt of the holy Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures which was written in after times.</p>
            <p>
               <label>Naylers Anſwer</label> But <hi>Nayler</hi> with a loud voice, ſtill cried out, liar, liar, is not God and his word all one? and bad the people beare witneſſe, hee ſaith God and his word are not all one.</p>
            <p>
               <label>Mr Bourn.</label> For Reply, We diſtinguiſh there is a unity of agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, ſo God and his written word are all one, and a unity of Eſſence or Being, ſo God and his written word, the Scripture, are not all one.</p>
            <p>
               <label>Mr Gardiners Argument.</label> Mr <hi>Gardiner</hi> Miniſter of <hi>Eckinton,</hi> being preſent, when he ſaw him ſo audaciouſly impudent, called to <hi>Nayler</hi> to hearken to an Argument to the contrary;
<pb facs="tcp:62479:9" rendition="simple:additions"/>which was to this effect. Whatſoever is all one with God, is eternall, but the holy Scripture or written word is not eternall, therefore it is not all one with God.</p>
            <p>
               <label>Naylers Anſwer</label> The Quaker <hi>Nayler</hi> preſently cried out in a ſcorn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full manner, away liar, away, ſtop thy mouth, the word is eternall, and God is eternall. And one of his fellow Quakers that ſtood by <hi>Nayler,</hi> called Mr <hi>Gardiner</hi> lyar, lyar, both with a loud voice, ſtop thy mouth, thou art a liar, thou art a liar.</p>
            <p>But let any indifferent man but read and conſider the Argument, and ſee if the Quaker be not proved the liar, and juſtly deſerved that ſhame himſelfe, which he ſo unjuſtly caſt upon Mr <hi>Gardiner,</hi> and the other Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters.</p>
            <p>Then Mr <hi>Godfrey Watkinſon</hi> of <hi>Brampton</hi> (an under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding Gentleman not a Miniſter) being preſent,
<note place="margin">Mr Godfrey Watkinſon of Brampton Moor neer Cheſterfield</note> cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led to <hi>Nayler,</hi> and told him he had loſt the Queſtion, and he himſelfe was the liar; for even now he ſaid the letter or written word was in time, and ſo not eternall, and now he ſaith the word is eternall, and God and his word is all one, when as the Queſtion and A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>gument is about the written word, which is not eternall, and therfore he was the lyar, &amp; loſt the Queſtion, or words to this effect (for I cannot remember every particular, but I endeavour to keep the ſence and words as well as I can remember.)</p>
            <p>
               <label>Naylers Anſwer</label> But <hi>Nayler</hi> kept on his loud mouthed pace, and gave Mr <hi>Watkinſon</hi> ſome unfit diſreſpective ſpeeches, and ſaid he owned the Spirit ſpeaking in holy men to bee the Judge, but would not own the Spirit of God ſpeak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in the Scriptures.</p>
            <p>
               <label>Mr Bournes Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply.</label> Mr <hi>Bourn</hi> began to preſſe other Arguments, but <hi>Nay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler</hi> would not hearken, but cried, ſtop thy mouth, liar, liar. Then Mr <hi>Bourne</hi> called to another Queſtion.</p>
            <p>But let any man truly conſider the Arguments, and ſee if <hi>Naylers</hi> mouth was not moſt fit to be ſtopped, and if <hi>Nayler</hi> was not the great liar, accuſing others
<pb facs="tcp:62479:10" rendition="simple:additions"/>wrongfully for that, of which hee was ſo juſtly guilty himſelfe.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Nayler</hi> did not then give his anſwer to the Queſtion in writing, but ſent it to us the day after the Diſputati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; In which he falſely applieth divers places of Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, to prove (if he could) that it is not the Spirit of God ſpeaking in the holy Scriptures, but the Spirit in holy men that is the chiefe Judge of Controverſies of Faith. I ſhall only in briefe, give ſome anſwer to his Allegation of Scripture, and ſome obſervations by the way, and then proceed to the ſecond Queſtion.</p>
            <p n="1">
               <label>Naylers Allega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</label> 1. The firſt Scripture <hi>Nayler</hi> alledgeth, is that, <hi>Exod.</hi> 18.16. <hi>When they have any matter</hi> (ſaith <hi>Moſes) they come to me, and I judge between one and another,</hi> &amp;c. Therefore thinks <hi>Nayler,</hi> it is not the Spirit ſpeaking in the Scriptures, but the Spirit ſpeaking in men, that judgeth. To which for anſwer.</p>
            <p>
               <label>Reply.</label> Firſt, I obſerve with what ſpirit the Quaker doth agree in this Allegation,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Cardinalis Bel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larmin. de judi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce Controverſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>arii fidei. lib.</hi> 3. <hi>cap.</hi> 3.</note> and this is with the Spirit of Antichriſt in Cardinall <hi>Bellarmine,</hi> who brings the ſelfe ſame place of Scripture, to prove an outward Judge of Controverſies of Faith, and to bee interpre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of the holy Scripture.</p>
            <p>The Queſtion he propoſeth is, whether the interpre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation of Scripture, be to be ſought from ſome one viſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble common Judge, which he affirmeth, and endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vours to prove from this Scripture; That as <hi>Moſes</hi> did anſwer to all doubts ariſing about the Law of God, ſo there muſt be an outward viſible Judge of all Contro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſies: And this is the Church, and the Spirit in the Church, or in the chiefe Paſtor (the Pope) with his Councill of Paſtours (ſaith <hi>Bellarmine</hi>) and the Spirit ſpeaking in holy men (ſaith <hi>Nayler</hi>) that is, in himſelfe, and his fellow Quaker: And thus you may ſee, from whom the Quakers received this Doctrine, even from the popiſh ſeducing Jeſuits, or ſome ſeduced <hi>Socinians,</hi> or other Heretickes, who ſeeke to diſgrace the holy Scriptures, that they may more eaſily ſet forth their
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:62479:10" rendition="simple:additions"/>owne errours with faire pretences of the ſpirit. But to anſwer Cardinall <hi>Bellarmine</hi> and <hi>James Nayler</hi> both together.</p>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>Moſes</hi> was an extraordinary man, and had an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traordinary meaſure of the Spirit, and yet <hi>Moſes</hi> did not take upon him an infallibility of Spirit and Judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, but did make known to the people, the ſtatutes of God, and his lawes. Thus, what God had or did re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veale, that was the Judge, not his own Spirit, nor any Spirit in him, but the voice of God in his law, or Gods own direction to end the Controverſie. This is evident, if you conſult theſe places of Scripture, which wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe what <hi>Moſes</hi> did in the cauſe of the womans ſon that curſed God, <hi>Lev.</hi> 24.
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Lev.</hi> 24.11, 12, 13, 14.</note> And about receiving the Paſſeover by the men that had touched the dead body of a man, <hi>Num.</hi> 6.9.
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Numb.</hi> 9.7, 8. <hi>Numb.</hi> 32.33, 34, 15, 32.</note> And concerning the man that gathered ſticks upon the Sabbath day, <hi>Numb.</hi> 15. he conſults with God in all thoſe. Thus <hi>Moſes</hi> and holy men before the Law written, they enquire of God to know his mind and pleaſure, and follow that which God taught them. But after the Law, and word and will of God was written, then to the Law and to the Teſtimony, <hi>If they speake not according to this, it is be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they have no light in them,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iſaiah</hi> 8.20.</note> as the Prophet <hi>Iſaiah</hi> doth witneſſe.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Obſerve what matters they were which <hi>Moſes</hi> did judge, they were not matters of Faith, but matters of Fact, Controverſies between man and man, he did judge between one and another (ſaith that Text) which <hi>Nayler</hi> himſelfe alledgeth nothing to the purpoſe (if he ſpeak of the Queſtion) For this is whether the Spirit of God ſpeaking in the Scriptures,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Exod.</hi> 18.16.</note> be the chiefe Judge of controverſies of Faith, not of actions between man and man. And this the Reader, whoſe eies are open, may eaſily diſcerne that this place of Scripture will neither fit Cardinall <hi>Bellarmine</hi> a Papiſt, nor <hi>James Nayler</hi> a Quaker. <hi>Nayler</hi> doth alledge divers other Scriptures of the ſame nature, to the ſame purpoſe; As
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:62479:11" rendition="simple:additions"/>that in <hi>Solomons</hi> prayer,
<note place="margin">1 <hi>Kin.</hi> 3.9.</note> 1 <hi>Kin.</hi> 3. That God would give him an underſtanding heart, that he might judge Gods people, to which the former anſwer may give full ſatis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction.</p>
            <p n="3">3.
<note place="margin">1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 2, 15, 16.</note> 
               <hi>Nayler</hi> alledgeth that of the Apoſtle, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 2. He that is ſpirituall judgeth all things, yet he himſelfe is judged of no man; for who hath known the mind of the Lord that he might inſtruct him? but we have the mind of Chriſt. Therefore (if <hi>Nayler</hi> may judge) it is not the Spirit of God ſpeaking in the Scriptures, but the Spirit ſpeaking in ſuch ſpirituall men as he is, which is the chiefe Judge of Controverſies of Faith. And herein the Quaker exceeds Cardinall <hi>Bellarmine</hi> by far; for the popiſh Cardinall would have infallibility of ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, only in the Pope and his company; but the Quaker maketh every particular ſpirituall man, a ſpirituall Pope, to be a chiefe Judge of Controverſies of Faith, otherwiſe <hi>Naylers</hi> Scripture is nothing to the Queſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, for the Queſtion is not concerning a private inferi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our, or particular Judge, but concerning a chiefe Judge of Controverſies of Faith, as <hi>Nayler</hi> himſelfe repea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth it. Queſtion the firſt. To give an anſwer to this and divers other Scriptures alledged by <hi>Nayler.</hi> But that he cannot away with a Diſtinction, he might know that there is a twofold Judge of Controverſies. Firſt, A Magiſteriall Judge (as I may ſo call it) a ſupreme higheſt directing publike Judge, to judge and diſcerne and direct, and finally, ſentence in the Church, all Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troverſies of Faith. And this is the holy Scriptures, and the Spirit of God ſpeaking in the Scriptures, to which Chriſt himſelfe did appeale and direct his hearers, to appeale unto in that great Controverſie of Faith, <hi>John</hi> 5.39. <hi>Search the Scriptures, for in them ye think to have eternall life, and they are they that testifie of me</hi> (which we noted before.)</p>
            <p>Againe, there is a Miniſteriall, inferiour, more private Judge of ſpirituall things, and ſo of Controverſies of Faith. And this may be every particular ſpirituall rege<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerate
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:62479:11"/>man or Chriſtian, according to the meaſure of that light of the Spirit and grace of Faith he hath recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved from Chriſt, and for the ſatisfaction of his owne conſcience, by the light of the Spirit ſpeaking in the Scriptures, and the light of Chriſt within him, he may ſo far as he is able, judge of opinions and doctrines of men, whether they agree to the doctrine of Chriſt in the holy Scriptures, I ſay to the ſatisfaction of a man or womans owne conſcience, in what they are to believe; yea thoſe to whom God hath given a more excellent meaſure of underſtanding in the myſtery of Chriſt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vealed in the Scriptures; theſe may in ſome meaſure judge, or be inferiour Judges of ſpirituall things, and of private mens opinions in the Controverſies of Faith; For the Spirit of the Prophets,
<note place="margin">1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 14.32.</note> is ſubject to the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets; but all private ſpirits of men in the world, yea the Pope himſelfe and all the Quakers, they are and muſt bee ſubject one day to the voice of Gods Spirit ſpeaking in the holy Scriptures, and that word of Chriſt recorded in holy Scriptures, ſhall judge them all at the laſt day, witneſſe our Saviour himſelfe, <hi>John</hi> 12.48. The Quaker abuſeth other places of holy Scripture. But the Anſwers I have given, may ſatisfie any under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding Reader; I ſhal name only one more from <hi>Nay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler</hi> and his fellow Quakers, which ſeems to conclude a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Scriptures excellency and authority, of being chiefe Judge of Controverſies of Faith, calling the holy Scriptures a dead letter, and the letter that killeth all, to diſcountenance the credit of the Scriptures, &amp; to exalt their owne private ſpirit. The place of Scripture they pervert, is that of the Apoſtle, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 3.6. Who hath made us able Miniſters of the New Teſtament, not of the letter, but of the Spirit, for the letter killeth, but the Spirit giveth life. I might anſwer at large, &amp; ſhew how the letter is taken in ſeverall places of Scripture, and evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence the falſhood of <hi>Naylers</hi> application of this place alſo; but in briefe. The letter is taken 1. Propperly for the firſt Elements or beginnings of learning for the let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:62479:12" rendition="simple:additions"/>in ſeverall languages, from which by ſpelling and putting together, are made ſyllables, and words and ſentences, in and by which the mind of God and men is held forth to our underſtanding, as in thoſe letters of Greek and Latine and Hebrew, which were written over Chriſt upon his Croſſe, <hi>Luke</hi> 23.38. And theſe letters may be called dead letters, becauſe of themſelves they ſignifie nothing to declare the mind of the writer, except they be joined and put together in<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> ſyllables words, and ſentences.</p>
            <p>Againe, Improperly and more generally, letters are taken ſeverall waies in Scripture, for Epiſtles private or publick,
<note place="margin">2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 3.6.</note> 
               <hi>&amp;c.</hi> And in that place alledged, The letter kil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth. The Apoſtle doth ſpeak of the Law which he op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſeth to the Goſpell, which is the miniſtration of the Spirit, as will appear plainly, if the Chapter be truly loo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked into, yea the Law it ſelfe doth not properly kill of it ſelfe, but is ſaid to kill when men break it, and ſo are become ſubject to death by ſinning againſt it;
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rom.</hi> 7.12, 13. <hi>Rom.</hi> 6.27. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 119.50.</note> for the wages of ſinne is death, otherwiſe the Law and word of God doth quicken, as <hi>David</hi> found by experience, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 119. And the written words of God, are lively oracles,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Acts</hi> 7.38. <hi>Heb.</hi> 4.12. 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3.16, 17</note> as the bleſſed Martyr <hi>Stephen</hi> witneſſed; yea mighty in operation and able to make us wiſe to ſalva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and therefore moſt fit to be the chiefe Judge of Controverſies of Faith, whatſoever the deluding Qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kers pretend to the contrary. Thus I have done with the firſt Queſtion, I come now to the ſecond Que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion.</p>
            <p>
               <label>Mr Bourns Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument.</label> The ſecond Queſtion: Whether the private Spirit in the Pope, or in any Quaker, be the chiefe Judge of Controverſies of Faith. This was denyed, and Mr <hi>Bourne</hi> proved the negative by this Argument. No Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit which is ſubject to tryall it ſelfe, can be the chiefe Judge of Controverſies of Faith; but the private Spirit in the Pope, or in any Quaker, is ſubject to tryall it ſelf, therefore the private Spirit in the Pope, or in any Qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ker, cannot be the chiefe Judge of any Controverſies of
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:62479:12"/>Faith. The firſt propoſition was not denied; and the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond is witneſſed, 1 <hi>John</hi> 4. <hi>Beloved, believe not eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry spirit, but try the spirits whether they be of God, for many falſe Prophets are gone out into the world.</hi> And here you may ſee the Evangeliſt giveth a generall rule for Chriſtians to try the ſpirit, all ſpirits in any man, yea all that pretend to the Spirit of God, as the Pope and the Quakers doe, therefore their ſpirits are to be tried, and ſo are not fit to be chiefe Judges of Controverſies of Faith.</p>
            <p>
               <label>Naylers Anſwer</label> 
               <hi>James Nailer</hi> wrangled about the Spirit, but gave no ſatisfying anſwer to the Argument, but ſaid the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit was not a private ſpirit, if he was but in one againſt a hundred, and ſaid the Spirit was in them, and he was Judge in them, as if the Spirit in the Quaker were a publick infallible Spirit, and ſo fit to be the chief Judge of Controverſies of Faith, which cannot be; for if the Spirit of the Prophets be ſubject to the Prophets,
<note place="margin">1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 14.32.</note> then much more the Spirit in the Pope, or in any Quaker, ſubject to tryall, and therefore they cannot bee the chiefe Judges of Controverſiies of Faith.</p>
            <p>
               <label>
                  <hi>Mr Bourns</hi> 2 <hi>Argument.</hi>
               </label> Then Mr <hi>Bourne</hi> preſſed a ſecond Argument. No Spirit which is a Spirit of Errour, lying and falſe accuſation, is or can be a chiefe Judge of Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troverſies of Faith. But the Spirit in the Quaker, and in <hi>James Nayler</hi> in particular, is a Spirit of Errour, lying and falſe accuſation, therefore that Spirit in them, can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be a chiefe Judge of Controverſies of Faith. The firſt propoſition is cleare, becauſe a chiefe Judge muſt and ought to have in him a Spirit, not of errour, lying and falſe accuſation, but a Spirit of truth and righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſſe, that he may bee directed to give true judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and not to wreſt or give wrong ſentence; for this is contrary to the Law of God, <hi>Exod</hi> 23.6, 7. Thou ſhalt not wreſt the judgement of the poor in his cauſe, and keep the farre from a falſe matter, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Therefore a Spirit of lying, and Errour, and falſe accuſation, is not fit to be a chiefe Judge of Controverſies, eſpecially not
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:62479:13"/>of Controverſies of Faith. And for the ſecond propoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, that the Spirit in the Quaker, and in <hi>James Nay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler</hi> in particular, is a Spirit of Errour, lying and falſe ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſation. Mr <hi>Bourne</hi> proved it by theſe Arguments.</p>
            <p>
               <label>Mr Bournes Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument.</label> Whatſoever Spirit did or doth affirme, and falſely accuſe the Miniſters of Chriſt in <hi>England,</hi> that they erre and are falſe Teachers, becauſe they ſay, the books of <hi>Matthew, Marke, Luke</hi> and <hi>John,</hi> are the Goſpell, that is a Spirit of Errour, lying and falſe accuſation. But the Spirit that is in <hi>James Nayler,</hi> and ſome of his fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low Quakers, did or doth accuſe the Miniſters of Chriſt in <hi>England,</hi> that they erre, and are falſe Teachers, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they affirme the books of <hi>Matthew, Marke, Luke</hi> and <hi>John,</hi> to be the Goſpell; therefore the Spirit in the Quakers, and in <hi>James Nayler</hi> in particular, is a Spirit of Errour, lying and falſe accuſation, and ſo not fit to be chiefe Judge of Controverſies of Faith. To evidence the ſecond propoſition, Mr <hi>Bourne</hi> did ſhew a book, the Title of it was concerning a threefold Antichriſt, or to that effect.
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>The ſame in effect by Rich<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ard Tarnworth, in his diſcovery of Faith, or ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of infideli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, page</hi> 13.</note> This was ſet out by ſome Quaker, and in page the 13. in the very leafe, in which beginneth a Letter of <hi>James Naylers,</hi> to ſeverall friends about <hi>Wake<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>field,</hi> when <hi>Nayler</hi> was priſoner at <hi>Appleby.</hi> There is Printed this falſe accuſation of the Miniſters in <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> as of Errour, becauſe they ſay the books of <hi>Mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thew, Marke, Luke</hi> and <hi>John,</hi> are the Goſpell, or con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine the glad tidings of ſalvation through Jeſus Chriſt, therefore the Quakers are not fit to be the chiefe Jud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges of Controverſies of Faith</p>
            <p>
               <label>Naylers Anſwer</label> 
               <hi>Nayler</hi> anſwered, hee did owne that Letter writ to his friends about <hi>Wakefield,</hi> and ſaid the books of <hi>Mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thew, Marke, Luke</hi> and <hi>John</hi> were not the Goſpell, but Chriſt was the Goſpell.</p>
            <p>
               <label>Mr Bourns Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply.</label> Mr <hi>Bourne</hi> went on to prove, that the books of <hi>Mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thew, Marke, Luke</hi> and <hi>John,</hi> were the Goſpell by this Argument.</p>
            <p>Whatſoever book the Spirit of God by the mouth of the Evangeliſt <hi>Marke,</hi> calleth the Goſpell; that is the
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:62479:13" rendition="simple:additions"/>Goſpel; but the Spirit of God by the mouth of the Evan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geliſt, <hi>Marke,</hi> calleth the book of <hi>Marke</hi> the Goſpell, therefore that book of <hi>Marke</hi> is the Goſpell. The firſt propoſition is unqueſtionable, The ſecond is witneſſed,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Marke</hi> 1.1.</note> 
               <hi>Marke</hi> 1.1. The beginning of the Goſpell of Jeſus Chriſt, the Sonne of God, as it is written in the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets. Obſerve firſt, That the Evangeliſt affirmeth, that the Goſpel was written in the Prophets. Secondly, that he calleth the beginning of that book, the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of the Goſpell; not that the Goſpell was not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, for the Goſpell was preached to <hi>Adam</hi> and <hi>Eve</hi> in Paradiſe, after the Fall,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Gen.</hi> 3.15.</note> 
               <hi>But the ſeed of the woman ſhall break the ſerpents head;</hi> but that it was the beginning of that book of the Goſpell, of that hiſtory of Chriſt, and declaration of ſalvation by Chriſt Jeſus. For what is the Goſpell, but good newes or good tidings of a Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour, as that Angell ſpeaketh, <hi>Luke</hi> 2.10. And good tidings of Chriſt, is not Chriſt himſelfe, and ſo the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpell is not Chriſt himſelfe, but good newes of ſalvation by Chriſt. This is the book of <hi>Marke,</hi> the Goſpell; and thus are the books of <hi>Matthew, Luke</hi> and <hi>John</hi> the Goſpell; and the Quaker denying this, and accuſing the Miniſters of Chriſt, as of Errour; for affirming it, this aſſertion is plainely proved, that the Spirit in the Qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ker, is a Spirit of Errour, lying and falſe accuſation, and ſo not fit to be the Judge of Controverſies of Faith.</p>
            <p>
               <label>Naylers Reply.</label> 
               <hi>Nayler</hi> had nothing to anſwer, but lyar, lyar, hold thy tongue, and ſit downe, for Chriſt is the Goſpell, the books of <hi>Matthew, Marke, Luke</hi> and <hi>John,</hi> are not the Goſpell.</p>
            <p>
               <label>Mr Bournes Argument.</label> Mr <hi>Bourne</hi> began to preſſe another Argument out of a booke of one <hi>Nicolas Cowlings,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Nicol. Cowling his word to <hi>52</hi> London Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters, p. <hi>15,</hi> &amp;c.</note> A word to the 52 <hi>London</hi> Miniſters, pages 15, 16. whereing he blaſphe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mouſly compareth Chriſt that dyed at <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> to a woodden leg. Let me be bold, ſaith he, to impart unto you my former experience in the myſtery of Chriſt. I thought a long while, a faith in Chriſt that died at <hi>Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruſalem,</hi> was the top gallant of a Chriſtian; but ſince it
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:62479:14"/>doth appeare,
<note place="margin">I Anſwer, There was a twofold Faith in the perſon of Chriſt. <hi>1.</hi> Erring of an outward Redemption from Roman ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ranny, of which Luke <hi>24 21.</hi> Acts <hi>1.16. 2.</hi> True Faith of an eternall Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demption from ſinne, &amp;c. and purchaſe of li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternall happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe for his peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple in Heaven, of which, Mat. <hi>1.21.</hi> Iohn <hi>1.29, 6, 47, 14, 1, 2, 3.</hi> The Erring faith died with Chriſt, but the true faith in Chriſts perſon, did not dye, as the Blaſphemer imagineth.</note> &amp;c. that faith the Diſciples had in the perſon of Chriſt, died with him, &amp;c. therefore it is Chriſt in the myſtery that will ſave. A woodden legge (ſaith he) that is tyed on, may do ſome ſervice, but it is the legge naturall that is uſefull for all occaſions. Thus doth this blaſphemer, make Chriſt our Saviour that died for us at <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> but as a woodden legge. But it is not that Chriſt that died at <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> mighty to ſave, not only by the work of ſanctification in us by his Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit through Faith to purifie our hearts, but by the worke of juſtification by his blood, and merits of his death and paſſion, by which he hath made our peace, even by the blood of his croſſe, and righteouſneſſe imputed to us for our juſtification before God, as by our holineſſe and good workes, we are declared to be juſtified before men: For God made him to be ſinne for us, who knew no ſinne, that we might be made the righteouſneſſe of God in him. But this Spirit in this deceived Quaker, or Erring Sectary, who glories in his perfection, and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gracefully calleth Chriſt that died at <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> a woodden legge, it is an Erring ſpirit, and therefore not fit to be judge of Controverſies of Faith.</p>
            <p>
               <label>Naylers Anſwer</label> 
               <hi>James Nayler</hi> would give no Anſwer to this, but ſaid he would not anſwer for any but himſelfe. Yet certainly <hi>James Nayler</hi> needed not then to have diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>owned that, or denied to anſwer; for it is nothing but what he himſelfe did owne before,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Read the Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect Phariſee, p.</hi> 8. <hi>poſition.</hi> 5.</note> as appeares by that expreſſion of his, in a Letter ſent by him to one in <hi>Lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſhire;</hi> That he that expected to be ſaved by him that died at <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> ſhould be deceived. This witneſsed by thoſe reverend Divines, who writ that book, called the Perfect Phariſee. And it ſeemeth it is their common opinion, as may appeare by that ſpeech of another Qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ker neer <hi>Briſtoll,</hi> who ſaid, he was not ſuch a foole, as to hope to be ſaved by Jeſus Chriſt that died at <hi>Jeru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſalem</hi> ſixteen hundred yeares agoe,
<note place="margin">Mr Farmer in his myſtery of godlineſſe and ungodlineſſe.</note> witneſsed by Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verend Mr <hi>Farmer,</hi> a Reverend Miniſter in <hi>Bristol.</hi> This ſpirit in the Quaker cannot be the chiefe Judge of Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troverſies of Faith.</p>
            <pb n="17" facs="tcp:62479:14" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>
               <label>Mr Billingsleys Argument.</label> Then Mr John <hi>Billingſley</hi> to prove that the Spirit in the Quakers, and in <hi>James Nayler</hi> in particular, was a lying ſcandalizing Spirit, and ſo not fit to be Judge of Controverſies of Faith, brought an Argument to this purpoſe.</p>
            <p>That Spirit whatſoever that did or doth affirm, that Bul-baiting, ſwearing, curſing, and ſuch like, are the fruits of <hi>John Billingsley</hi>'s Miniſtrie, that is a lying ſcan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dalizing Spirit; but the Spirit that is in thee <hi>James Nay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler,</hi> or thou thy ſelfe <hi>James Nayler,</hi> diddeſt affirme, that Bul-baiting, ſwearing, curſing, and ſuch like, is or are the fruits of <hi>John Billingſley</hi>'s Miniſtery, therefore thy Spirit is a lying ſcandalizing Spirit, and ſo not fit to be Judge of Controverſies of Faith. For the firſt propoſition, I <hi>John Billingſley</hi> doe appeale to all the Congregations which have heard me preach in <hi>Che<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterfield,</hi> or elſe where, if ever I preached any ſuch do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine, or did ever countenance any ſuch thing neither was I at home at <hi>Chesterfield,</hi> when the Bul-baiting was, nor did I know any thing of it, but am altogether innocent. And for the ſecond propoſition. That thou <hi>James Nayler</hi> diddeſt falſely accuſe me, <hi>John Billings<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ley,</hi> it is evident by thy owne hand writing in this pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per, which thou diddeſt ſend to me, ſubſcribed with thy name, in which are theſe words, <hi>viz.</hi> This day is the fruits of thy Miniſtry manifeſt in the open ſtreets, a multitude gathered together, to ſport themſelves in ſetting one of the Creatures of God againſt another to torment &amp; thy people thou teacheſt, whooting, yelling,
<note place="margin">Mr Billingsley did then read theſe words, written by Iames Nayler to him, &amp;c.</note> ſwearing, curſing, and blaſpheming the dreadfull name of God; Is this thy Miniſtry? <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Thus diddeſt thou falſly accuſe me and my Miniſtry; therefore thy Spirit is a lying, and falſe accuſing Spirit, and ſo not fit to be the chiefe Judge of Controverſies of Faith.</p>
            <p>
               <label>Naylers Anſwer</label> To which <hi>Nayler</hi> ſaid, he did owne that paper, and ſhuffled to excuſe himſelfe, and ſaid, he did not ſay ſo, but that the people to whom he did preach, were ſo doing, <hi>viz.</hi> ſwearing, curſing, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="18" facs="tcp:62479:15" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>
               <label>Mr Billingsley's Reply.</label> But Mr <hi>Billingſley</hi> read the paper to all the congre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation, wherein it did appeare, that <hi>Nayler</hi> had writ, that Bul-baiting, ſwearing and curſing, were the fruits of Mr <hi>Billingsley</hi>'s Miniſtry.
<label>Naylers Anſwer</label> At which <hi>Nayler</hi> knew not what to ſay for himſelfe, but ſtill perſiſted with an audacious face to juſtifie himſelfe, and called Mr <hi>Bil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lingsley</hi> liar, liar, and bad him hold his tongue.</p>
            <p>
               <label>Mr Billingsley's Reply.</label> Upon which Mr <hi>Billingsley</hi> ſaid, what a deſperate fellow art thou, ſo ſhameleſſely to deny that which thou haſt writ with thy owne hand, and doſt now a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine prove thy ſelfe to be a lyar, and a falſe accuſer, and wilt not confeſſe thy Errour, or to that purpoſe.</p>
            <p>
               <label>Naylers Anſwer</label> But <hi>Nayler</hi> vapoured, and called Mr <hi>Billingsley</hi> lyar, and ſaid he had accuſed him to be a lyar, and a perſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor of the Miniſters of Chriſt. <label>Mr Billingsley's Reply.</label> But Mr <hi>Billingsley</hi> did juſtifie, that <hi>Nayler</hi> was a lyar, and a perſecutor, and that his falſe accuſation was a perſecution, or to that effect. And I might now add, well ſo he might; For may not all men ſee, that the Quakers and <hi>James Nay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler</hi> himſelfe, are as malicious perſecutors of the Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters of Chriſt in <hi>England,</hi> as ever they had? And would they not be as bloody as ever any, if it lay in their pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er? witneſſe their cruell threatnings both in their prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted Pamphlets and by word of mouth againſt us, wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe their labouring by all meanes, to pull downe the very Calling and Miniſteriall Office, witneſſe their en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavour to hinder the people to pay us any mainte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance, though due unto us both by the Law of God and the Nation.
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ierem</hi> 18.18.</note> Do they not ſmite us with the tongue? as <hi>Jeremies</hi> enemies did him, and diſſwade our people from giving heed to any of our words; And what are theſe but perſecutions?
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rev.</hi> 12.10.</note> or what is perſecution if this be not? and who are lyars if theſe be none? and who is a diabolicall falſe accuſer,
<note place="margin">Iohn B<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nting en Elder of the Church in Aſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>over.</note> if <hi>James Nayler</hi> is not? <hi>John Bunting</hi> an honeſt Yeoman (of more true ſpirituall underſtanding, then many Quakers) ſitting by <hi>Nayler</hi> at this diſputation, writing in ſhort hand what <hi>Nayler</hi> ſaid, <hi>Nayler</hi> ſeeing him write, ſaid to him, thou writeſt
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:62479:15" rendition="simple:additions"/>lyes there: To whom <hi>John Bunting</hi> Replyed, <hi>Nayler,</hi> thou art the father of them then, for I write what thou ſpeakeſt. Whereupon I may obſerve and argue, what may be argued from what St <hi>Paul</hi> did affirme of the <hi>Cretians,</hi> and of the vain talkers, and deceivers amongſt them; That one of their owne Prophets ſaid, The <hi>Cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tians</hi> are alwaies lyars, evill beaſts, ſlow bellies, <hi>Tit.</hi> 1.
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Tit.</hi> 1.10, 11, 12.</note> And if the <hi>Cretians</hi> were lyars, then that Prophet was a lyar that ſaid ſo, becauſe he was a <hi>Cretian,</hi> and if the <hi>Cretians</hi> were not lyars, then he was a lyar for ſaying they were lyars when they were not. In like manner, if <hi>Iohn Bunting</hi> did write lies, then <hi>Nayler</hi> was and is a lyar, becauſe <hi>Iohn Bunting</hi> did write that which <hi>Nayler</hi> ſpake; and if <hi>Iohn Bunting</hi> did not write lies, then <hi>Iames Nayler</hi> is the lyar, becauſe he falſely accuſed <hi>Iohn Bun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting</hi> for writing lies, when he did not; ſo that <hi>Iames Nayler</hi> is proved the lyar out of his owne mouth and pen, and having a ſpirit of lying, he is not fit to be the chiefe Judge of Controverſies of Faith.</p>
            <p>Thus I have done with the Diſputation upon this Queſtion, Whether the private Spirit in the Pope, or in any Quaker, be the chiefe Judge of Controverſies of Faith. I ſhall only add one Argument more, and paſſe forwards.</p>
            <p>
               <label>Mr Bournes ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditionall Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</label> No Spirit that is a Spirit of Errour and Blaſphemy, is fit to be or can be the chiefe Judge of Controverſies of Faith. But the Spirit in <hi>Iames Nayler,</hi> and other Quakers, is a Spirit of Errour and Blaſphemy; There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Spirit in <hi>Iames Nayler,</hi> and other Quakers, is not fit, nor can be a chiefe Judge of Controverſies of Faith. For the firſt propoſition, certainly the Quakers themſelves will not deny it, and (if they doe deny it) no honeſt Chriſtian will deny it; and for the ſecond it may be witneſſed by theſe inſtances. 1. Blaſphemy againſt God, whileſt they doe affirme they are equall with God;
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>See Saules Er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rand to Damaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cus, p.</hi> 5, 6, 7, 8.</note> This was witneſsed againſt <hi>George Fox</hi> (as is confeſsed by <hi>Fox</hi> and <hi>Nayler,</hi> one or both) (If that Booke they call <hi>Sauls</hi> Errand to <hi>Damaſcus</hi> be theirs
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:62479:16"/>(as their proſelytes boaſt it is) and ſeek after it to learn their wicked doctrines. It was objected (ſay they) That <hi>George Fox</hi> profeſſed and owned that he was equall with God.
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> the Perfect Phariſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> p.</hi> 3.</note> And in the: Perfect Phariſee it is witneſsed, That <hi>George Fax</hi> being asked by Dr. <hi>Marſhall</hi> in the preſence of two Juſtices of Peace in <hi>Lancaſhire,</hi> namely, Mr <hi>Thomſon</hi> and Mr <hi>Lawry,</hi> whether he did believe himſelfe to be equall with God; the ſaid <hi>Fox</hi> in anſwer thereunto, poſitively affirmed, thus I am ſaith he equall with God; and this was depoſed by Dr <hi>Marſhall</hi> and Mr <hi>Altham</hi> School-Maſter of <hi>Lancaſter,</hi> at the gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall Seſſions in <hi>Weſtmerland,</hi> and was depoſed againe before the honourable Judge <hi>Puleſton</hi> at <hi>Lancaſter</hi> the next Aſſiſes after, witneſs that booke called the Perfect Phariſee,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Perfect Phari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſee by Mr T<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mas W<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ld, Mr R<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>chard Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>, Mr Samuel Ham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mond, Mr Willi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>am <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap>, Mr Will. D<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>rant. The Perfect Phar<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſee. p</hi> 3. <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </note> made by thoſe five Reverend Divines nere New Caſtle, p. 3 which declares part of the Quakers blaſphemies, in the page before recited. And in the ſame book it is witneſsed againſt <hi>Iames Nayler,</hi> that he be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing asked by <hi>William Baldwinſon</hi> of <hi>Underbarrow</hi> in <hi>Weſtmorland,</hi> whether he believed that any could be as holy. Juſt, and good as God himſelfe, <hi>Nayler</hi> anſwered, that he himſelfe was as holy, juſt, and good, as God himſelfe. And this Mr <hi>Baldw<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nſon</hi> did offer to depoſe to Colonell <hi>Briggs,</hi> who is a man fearing God, and of e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minent truſt in the Common-wealth; and what is this but preſumptuous blaſphemy, both in <hi>Fox</hi> and <hi>Nayler,</hi> ſo proudly to boaſt of their owne perfection, and that not by the imputed righteouſneſs of Chriſt, for that they deny, but by their own inherent holineſs (which they pretend to be Chriſt within them) and yet ſo baſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to manifeſt themſelves notorious lyars?
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>The briefe vola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the irre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion of the Northern Qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>k<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>rs wherein their h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 chunk">
                        <desc>…</desc>
                     </gap>d principles and practiſes, do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrines and manners are diſcovered, read page</hi> 24 25.</note> As in that Pamphlet, called <hi>Saul's</hi> Errand to <hi>Damaſcus,</hi> in which there are a hundred untruths, as may be proved by a hundred witneſses, teſtified in that booke called A Briefe Relation of the irreligion of the Northern Qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kers, page 24. Many of them (ſaith that Author) will be as ready to ſay and unſay any thing, as if lying were a vertue, and they make no conſcience (ſaith he) of
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:62479:16"/>raiſing falſe reports againſt thoſe eſpecially, who doe any way oppoſe them; and he goeth on further. Thus wholly by lies, lying doctrines: lying wonders, lying reports, they endeavour to build up the Kingdome of the Father of lyes amongſt us. Thus farre and further that reverend Author. I might add many more of their errours lies, and abominable blaſphemies: But theſe are ſufficient to witneſſe the Spirit in <hi>James Nayler,</hi> and divers of his fellow Quakers, to be a Spirit of Errour and Blaſphemy, and therefore not fit to be chiefe Jud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges of Controverſies of Faith. Other their Errours and Blaſphemies are ſo abominable, that I hold them fitter to be buried in ſilence, then to rake them up out of the Devils dung-hill, to be an odious noiſom ſtinke and of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence to the people of God.</p>
            <p>Now for <hi>Naylers</hi> anſwer, and his croſſe interroga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tories, upon this and other Queſtions. I have anſwered them fully in every particular, which with my Reply to his Quaeries and diſcoveries of many of his abomina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble lies, increaſed in my written hand, prepared for the Preſſe, to above threeſcore ſheets of paper, which I have ready by me, the which I was reſolved by Gods grace, to have printed in Defence of Chriſt, the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell, and the faithfull Goſpel-Miniſters of Chriſt in <hi>England,</hi> and their maintenance. But comming to <hi>London,</hi> I finde theſe things ſo ſufficiently anſwered, and truth ſo ſully ſatisfied againſt the Quakers and their errours, by ſo many godly and learned Divines, that I conceive to add more, is but to caſt water into the ſea; and therefore I have thought good to print only theſe few ſheets, and to let the reſt of my labours reſt un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>printed untill God ſhall give me a further call unto that worke. I now therefore proceed to the third Queſtion Diſputed.</p>
            <p>
               <label>
                  <hi>3</hi> Queſtion Diſputed.</label> Whether every man be bound to looke to the light within him as ſufficient for his ditection to attaine ſalvation? This we denyed.</p>
            <p>
               <label>The ſtate of the Queſtion.</label> The ſence of the Queſtion is, Whether every man
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:62479:17"/>and woman in the world, have a ſufficient light within them, for their direction to attaine eternall life, ſo as he or ſhee needeth not to looke to the outward light of the written word of God, or to the light of the Goſpell revealed in the holy Scriptures, or to any outward tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching by man whatſoever, although it be agreeable to the Scripture of truth.</p>
            <p>This in effect was the opinion of <hi>Nayler,</hi> as it is of divers of his fellow Quakers, witneſs <hi>Nayler</hi> himſelfe, in his anſwer in writing, ſent to us the day after the Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpute, and ſince printed. The light of Chriſt ſaith hee, which hath enlightned every man that commeth into the world, is ourlight, and to that is every one bound to look for direction to attaine Salvation, and that he affirmeth as ſufficient, or to that effect. And the ſame did <hi>Nayler</hi> affirm before, in his diſcourſe with Mr <hi>Will. Cole</hi> at <hi>Kendall;</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>See the Perfect Phariſee, the ſubſcription to the Epiſtle, and pages</hi> 17.18. <hi>Richard Tarn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worth, p.</hi> 51. <hi>&amp;c</hi>
               </note> To whom he ſaid that every man in the world had a light within him, ſufficient to guide them to ſalvation, and this he extended to the Indi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans that never heard the Goſpell, witneſſe that booke called the Perfect Phariſee, written by thoſe five Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verend Miniſters nere New Caſtle, named before. And thus <hi>James Nayler,</hi> and divers others of his fellow Quakers in other Pamphlets, which for brevity ſake I omit.</p>
            <p>
               <label>Mr Bournes Argument.</label> But I did prove the contrary by this Argument. No man whoſoever is darkneſſe, is bound to looke to the light within him, as ſufficient to direct him to attaine Salvation; but every naturall man is darkneſſe, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore no naturall man is bound to looke to the light within him, as ſufficient for his direction to attaine ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation, and ſo not every man that commeth into the world. The firſt propoſition is evident, becauſe it is in vaine to look for light in darkneſſe. And the ſecond propoſition is witneſſed by the Apoſtle <hi>Paul, Eph.</hi> 5.8. Ye were once darkneſſe (ſaith he) to the Epheſians, but now ye are light in the Lord. In the ſtate of nature corrupted by <hi>Adams</hi> Fall, they were darkneſſe, having
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:62479:17"/>their underſtandings darkened through the ignorance that was in them, becauſe of the blindneſſe of their minds. And what light then had theſe within them, ſufficient to direct them to Salvation; or what ſufficient light hath any naturall man in the world? and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore all are not bound to looke to the light within them, as ſufficient for their direction to attaine Salva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
            <p>
               <label>Naylers Anſwer</label> All <hi>Naylers</hi> anſwer was, it is falſe, it is falſe, lyar, lyar, all are enlightned, and have a light within them ſufficient to direct them to Salvation, or to that ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect. <label>Mr Billingsley's Argument:</label> And after ſome wranglings by <hi>Nayler,</hi> Mr <hi>Bil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lingsley</hi> called to <hi>Nayler</hi> to heare an Argument, and gave this, or to this effect.</p>
            <p>None of thoſe to whom <hi>Paul</hi> was ſent to turn them from darkneſſe to light, and from the power of Satan to God, had a light within them, to which they were bound to looke, as ſufficient to direct them to attaine Salvation. But there were ſome Gentiles, to whom <hi>Paul</hi> was ſent, to turn them from darkneſſe to light, and from the power of Satan to God; therefore ſome Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiles had not a light within them to which they could looke, as ſufficient to direct them to attaine Salvation, and ſo not every man in the world. The firſt propoſition is manifeſt, becauſe if thoſe Gentiles had a light within them ſufficient to direct them to attaine Salvation, then what needed the Lord to have ſent bleſſed <hi>Paul</hi> through ſo many dangers, to turne them from darkneſſe to light, and from the power of Satan to God. And for the ſecond, the Evangeliſt <hi>Luke</hi> doth witneſſe it,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Acts</hi> 26.17, 18.</note> 
               <hi>Acts</hi> 26. Delivering thee from the Gentiles, to whom I ſend thee to turne them from darkneſs to light, and from the power of Satan to God. And thus againe it is evident, that all have not a light within them ſufficient to direct them to ſalvation, and therefore are not bound to looke to that as a ſufficient light, which is weak and inſufficient, as the light of every naturall man is.</p>
            <p>
               <label>Nailers Anſwer.</label> To which Argument, <hi>Nayler</hi> gave his common An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer,
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:62479:18" rendition="simple:additions"/>crying out aloud as before, lyar, lyar, all have a light within them, to which they ought to looke as ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient to direct them to Salvation.</p>
            <p>
               <label>Iohn Buntings Argument.</label> Upon which <hi>Iohn Bunting</hi> of <hi>Aſhover,</hi> named be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, an underſtanding Chriſtian, ſitting neer <hi>Nayler,</hi> Replyed to him, Dead men have no light in them, but every naturall man is a dead man, dead in treſpaſses and ſins,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 2.1, 2, 3.</note> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s witneſseth the Apoſtle, <hi>Eph.</hi> 2. and what light is there then in a naturall dead man, ſufficient to direct him to attaine ſalvation?</p>
            <p>
               <label>Naylers Anſwer</label> 
               <hi>Nayler</hi> Anſwered not to the Argument, concerning naturall mens blindneſs, but ſaid Chriſt had enlightned all men,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iohn.</hi> 1.9.</note> and alledged that place, <hi>Iohn</hi> 1.9. He is that light that lightens every man that commeth into the world; and thence he would inferre, every man is en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lightned, and hath a light within him ſufficient to direct him to attaine Salvation, or to that purpoſe, ſo neer as I could remember.</p>
            <p>
               <label>Mr Bournes Anſwer to this Scipture, alled<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged, A firſt light.</label> Unto this Scripture I did then anſwer to this effect, by diſtinguiſhing of light, and ſaid, there was a two-fold light. The firſt the light of nature, the remnant of that created light of the knowledge of God in man, by which men might know ſo much of God by the Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rom.</hi> 1.19, 20.</note> as may make them without excuſe, <hi>Rom.</hi> 1.19. And which is a ſparke of light naturally in every mans conſcience,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rom.</hi> 2.14, 15.</note> 
               <hi>Rom.</hi> 2. And with this light Chriſt the Creator (God, equall with God the Father, by whom this light and all things were made) he doth enlighten every man that commeth into the world; that is into this habitable world, in which we dwell; and all that are borne into this world in their right mind and ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, Chriſt doth enlighten with this naturall light. But this light of nature, ſince the Fall, is ſo darkned, that al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though it may be ſufficient in ſome reſpects, to make men without excuſe;
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rom.</hi> 1.20.</note> yet it is not ſufficient to reveale Chriſt, or to give ſufficient direction to attaine Salva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion by Chriſt Jeſus, as that light which revealeth Chriſt in the Goſpell. Againe, there is a ſecond light,
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:62479:18" rendition="simple:additions"/>and this is the light of ſpeciall grace given outwardly by the preaching of the Word, and inwardly by the Spirit of God, by which a ſoule is enlightned with ſuch a ſpeciall light of the knowledge of the glory of God in the face of Jeſus Chriſt, as he owneth,
<note place="margin">2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 4 6, 7.</note> and by faith em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braceth Chriſt,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rom.</hi> 5.</note> not only as a Juſtifier by his blood and merits, but a Sanctifier by his Spirit and grace in the ſoule, and ſo a perfect Saviour both from ſinne here, and from wrath to come hereafter, as due to ſinne. And this in ward light of ſpeciall grace, every man (to whom God hath given it) is bound to look unto it in a ſpeciall manner; yet not ſo as to neglect the outward light of the Goſpell, revealed in the holy Scriptures, for the get<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting of more light, becauſe we know here but in part,
<note place="margin">1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 13 9, 10, 11, 12.</note> and therefore ſhould waite for more light of grace, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>till we come to enjoy a perfection of light in glory. Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe this ſpeciall light of grace held forth in the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpell, is not given to all, for all do not know the myſtery of the Goſpell; nor is it given unto all, witneſſe our Saviour,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mat.</hi> 13.11.</note> 
               <hi>To you it is given</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>to know the myſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries of the Kingdome of God, but to others it is not given.</hi> And the Evangeliſt, <hi>John</hi> himſelfe in the ſame Chapter,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iohn</hi> 1.9, 10, 11, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </note> in which he affirmeth, that Chriſt is the true light that lightneth every man that commeth into the world, in the very next verſe he affirmeth, that Chriſt was in the world, and the world did not know him; yea he came to his owne, and his owne received him not. But if all in the world had this ſpeciall light of grace within them, they would have known Chriſt;
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iohn</hi> 18.35.</note> yea if all his owne people, the people of the Jewes, his owne Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, had received this ſpeciall light of grace, they would have received Chriſt; But many of them were in blindneſſe, yea darkneſſe it ſelfe, and did not know Chriſt; for had they knowne him, they would not have, crucified the Lord of Glory, witneſſe the Apoſtle, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 2.7, 8. Th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> anſwer was delivered logically in more briefe termes, but to the ſame effect, and more fully and largely expreſsed now for weak brethrens ſakes, that
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:62479:19" rendition="simple:additions"/>they may more eaſily underſtand <hi>Naylers</hi> deceits in his anſwer, who gave that more largely alſo in his written paper, then at the Diſputation for that was commonly very ſhort; It is falſe, it is falſe, and lyar, lyar. And this was <hi>Naylers</hi> Reply to this Diſtinction of light given by me, It is falſe, lyar, hold thy peace and ſit downe, there is but one light that lightens every man that com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth into the world, and in a vapouring manner doub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led it againe, there is but one light which lightneth every man that commeth into the world.</p>
            <p>
               <label>M. Maud<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>y</label> Mr <hi>Maudſley</hi> (as I remember) Miniſter of <hi>Dron<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>field,</hi> ſitting neer <hi>Nayler,</hi> asked him what world he did meane, <label>Nayler. Queſtion.</label> 
               <hi>Nayler</hi> anſwered, there is but one world, and that is the world of men; he was asked againe, whether he himſelfe was in the world, or out of the world, <label>Anſwer.</label> to which <hi>Nayler</hi> anſwered, that he was out of the world; unto which Anſwer, ſome one replyed, it were well if thou waſt out of the world, that thou mighteſt not ſpread thy errours as thou doſt in the world. <hi>Nayler</hi> wrangled ſtill about the world, and ſaid, there was but one world, and that was the world of men, which were all enlightned. Then one that was neer <hi>Nayler,</hi> asked <hi>Nayler</hi> what world that was into which Chriſt came,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iohn</hi> 16.28.</note> when he came out from his Father, and which he left when he went to his Father againe. And <hi>Nayler</hi> ſhufied, and would have avoided the Queſtion; upon which there fell out a wrangling, and other paſsages impertinent to the Queſtion in hand, which for brevi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty I omit here, and ſhall remember them in my Ani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>madverſions upon <hi>Naylers</hi> falſe Relation. <label>Mr Bourne.</label> Whiles they were wrangling, Mr <hi>Bourne</hi> did call to <hi>Nayler</hi> to leave wrangling, and hearken to another Argument, to prove that all men had not a light within them, ſufficient to direct them to attaine ſalvation, and was giving forth an Argument. <label>Mr Moors Argument.</label> But Mr <hi>Moor</hi> Miniſter of <hi>Brampton,</hi> ſtept in and gave this Argument, or to this effect. If there be ſome men that have no light in them, then all men have not a light within them, ſufficient to direct them to at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:62479:19" rendition="simple:additions"/>ſalvation. But there are ſome men that have no light in them, witneſs the Prophet <hi>Iſaiah,</hi> chap. 8.20. <hi>To the Law and to the Testimony, if they ſpeak not ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to this rule, it is becauſe there is no light in them.</hi> Therefore all men have not a light within them, ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient to direct them to attaine ſalvation.</p>
            <p>
               <label>Naylers Anſwer</label> 
               <hi>James Nayler</hi> vapoured, and ſaid, that place made moſt againſt us: But he gave no anſwer to ſhew how that place did make againſt us, but cryed out, all are enlightned by Chriſt, and that light of Chriſt is in them all, lyars, lyars, all are enlightned. Thus in a proud con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temptuous manner, did <hi>Nayler</hi> behave himſelfe; and as his manner was when hee could not anſwer, turned aſide, and talked to thoſe that were about him, and at laſt affirmed againe, that all had a light within them, ſufficient to guide them to attaine ſalvation, <label>Naylers Argument.</label> becauſe Chriſt ſaid to the Phariſees, <hi>Luke</hi> 17.21. The Kingdome of God is within you, in you Phariſees, and therefore in all, and ſo the Kingdome of God being in all, all are ſufficiently enlightned to direct them to attaine ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation.</p>
            <p>
               <label>Mr Bournes Anſwer.</label> To which, Anſwer was given to this effect; That the Kingdome of God is taken diverſly in the holy Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures.</p>
            <p n="1">1. For the Kingdome of Gods power, which is Gods ſoveraignty over all the world, and this King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of God is in every creature, and in, and over eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry man in the world; he ſets up and puls downe,
<note place="margin">1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 2.6, 7, 8, <hi>&amp;c. Dan.</hi> 4.30, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </note> kils and maketh alive at his pleaſure, and ruleth, and over-ruleth all, when and how he will, and this Kingdome of God was in the Phariſees, as in all men whatſoever.</p>
            <p n="2">2. The Kingdome of God is taken for the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of Gods Grace, and this diverſly taken alſo. Firſt, for the outward adminiſtration of the comming and Kingdome of the Meſſiah Chriſt Jeſus, in the Goſpell; of which the Phariſees queſtioned Chriſt in that place, <hi>Luke</hi> 17.
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Luke</hi> 17.20. <hi>Gen.</hi> 49.10.</note> demanding when the Kingdome of God ſhould come, that is, the Kingdome of the Meſſiah,
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:62479:20" rendition="simple:additions"/>which was prophecied and promiſed ſhould come,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 2. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 45.6, 7. <hi>Luke</hi> 2.25, 26.</note> and which the Saints and people of God did expect and waite for; And <hi>John</hi> the <hi>Baptiſt</hi> (the forerunner of Chriſt) told the people this Kingdome was at hand. This Kingdome is called the Kingdome of Heaven,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mat.</hi> 3.2. <hi>Mat.</hi> 13.24, 44. <hi>Acts</hi> 1.3.</note> and it is taken for the Goſpel, and Goſpel. Adminiſtrations, and this Kingdome and comming of Chriſt, this King, not only the Scribes and Phariſees,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Luke</hi> 24.21.</note> but ſome of the Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciples, did think ſhould come in outward pompe and power, to deliver the Jewes from the tyranny of the Romans, under whom they were tributaries. But Chriſt giveth them anſwer in that 20 verſe.
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Luke</hi> 17 20.</note> The King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of Chriſt the Meſſiah (which they enquired after) commeth not with obſervation, or with outward pompe; but ſaith Chriſt, the Kingdome of God is with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in you, not individually or perſonally, as if the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of heaven (the Goſpell) and Chriſt the Meſſiah had been in every one of them particularly, or in every Phariſee; but collectively, or as they were a company of Phariſees, or people of the Jewes. The Kingdome of God is within you, or rather amongſt you, as the Greek word is well tranſlated in the margin of our Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles in that place. And thus Expoſitors agree, ye ſeeke the Meſſiah as if hee were abſent, when hee is in the middeſt of you,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Beza upon the Text. P<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſcator on that place. Thus Paſſor Iex con, &amp;c.</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>in medio veſtri intra gentem ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtram with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in your nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.</hi>
               </note> ſaith <hi>Beza.</hi> And <hi>Piſcator,</hi> The King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of God is in the middeſt of you, in the boſome of your Nation. The Kingdome of God is within you, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand it not as every one is looked upon, by and in himſelfe, but as one body of many people, collected or joined together in one body or Nation. And the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of God in this ſence, was in and amongſt the Phariſees and people, to whom Chriſt did preach at that time. Againe, the Kingdome of Grace is taken for the gifts and Graces of the Kingdome, or which Chriſt the King giveth to his ſubjects and ſervants, and by his Spirit worketh in them, as Knowledge, Faith, Love, Righteouſneſs, Peace, and Joy in the Holy Ghoſt, and ſuch like inward ſpirituall Riches, and Graces of the
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:62479:20"/>ſpirit, by which God doth rule and reigne in the heats of his children, and this Kingdome is in Gods Elect, his choſen and faithfull, and called ones,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rev.</hi> 17.14.</note> not only amongſt them, but in them; but this Kingdome or theſe graces of the Kingdome of Chriſt, the Meſſiah, and Chriſts Spirit, was not in the Phariſees, to whom Chriſt did preach, though it was amongſt them, in ſuch as were true beleevers, Gods faithfull ſervants. This Anſwer was delivered far ſhorter, but to this effect and purpoſe.</p>
            <p>
               <label>Naylers Reply.</label> But <hi>Nayler</hi> according to his accuſtomed manner, cried out, lyars, lyars, it is falſe, Chriſt ſpeaketh of the Kingdome of Grace, and that was in the Phariſees, and ſo in all, and all have a light in them, to which they may look, as ſufficient to guide them to Salvation; or to that effect.</p>
            <p>
               <label>Mr Bournes Reply.</label> Mr <hi>Bourne</hi> did Reply,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iohn</hi> 3.1. <hi>Iohn</hi> 19.38, 39</note> that ſome of the Phariſees may be were beleevers, as <hi>Nicodemus,</hi> who came to Jeſus by night, and was at coſt with <hi>Joſeph</hi> of <hi>Arima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thea,</hi> at the buriall of Chriſt, who was a Diſciple, though ſecretly for feare of the Jewes. And if this Kingdome of Grace was in any of the Phariſees, they muſt be ſuch as were beleevers, for other wiſe in unbe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leevers and wicked Phariſees, who kept men (to their power) from confeſſing of Chriſt to be the Meſſiah,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iohn</hi> 12.42.</note> in them Chriſt was not, nor the Kingdome, nor the graces of Chriſts Kingdome. For in unbeleevers, where ſinne, ruleth and reigneth in their mortall bodies, and they obey it in the luſts thereof, there or in their ſoules,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rom.</hi> 6.12, 16.</note> the Kingdome of Grace is not; for Chriſt and ſinne cannot reign both together in one ſoule. This anſwer was ſhorter likewiſe but to this intent.</p>
            <p>
               <label>Naylers Reply.</label> But <hi>Nayler</hi> would not yield the Queſtion for all this; but told the people the Kingdome of God was in the Phariſees, and we were lyars that denied it.</p>
            <p>
               <label>Mr Maud<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>y's Queſtion.</label> Mr <hi>Maudeſley</hi> (if my memory did not faile me) or ſome one neer him asked <hi>Nayler,</hi> what Kingdome that was, which Chriſt ſpake of after his reſurrection, <hi>Acts</hi>
               <pb n="30" facs="tcp:62479:21" rendition="simple:additions"/>1.
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Acts.</hi> 1.3.</note> He was ſeen of them forty daies, ſpeaking of the things pertaining to the Kingdome of God.</p>
            <p>
               <label>Naylers Reply.</label> 
               <hi>Nayler</hi> did not anſwer what that Kingdome was, but ſaid, Chriſt was not ſeene after his Aſcenſion. In which <hi>Nayler</hi> did miſtake; <label>Anſwer.</label> for it was not after Chriſts Aſcenſion, but after his reſurrection. After which it was demanded, what Kingdome Chriſt did ſpeake of <hi>Acts</hi> 1.</p>
            <p>
               <label>Reply of another to Nayler.</label> But ſome one neer <hi>Nayler</hi> Replied,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Acts</hi> 9.5, 17. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 9.1. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15.7, 8.</note> that Chriſt was ſeen after his Aſcenſion. For he was ſeen of <hi>Paul,</hi> as <hi>Paul</hi> himſelfe doth teſtifie. Am not I an Apoſtle, have I not ſeen the Lord? And laſt of all, he was ſeen of me, as one born out of due time, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label>Iames Naylers Anſwer.</label> 
               <hi>Nayler</hi> anſwered, Chriſt was ſeene, but he was ſeen inviſibly.</p>
            <p>
               <label>Reply.</label> To which one Replyed, that was a Bull or a ſence<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe Anſwer, for whatſoever is ſeen, muſt be ſeen vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſibly, in what manner ſoever it is ſeene, whether by the eie of the body, or by faith the eie of the ſoule. If we ſee him that is inviſible, as <hi>Moſes</hi> did; yet he is viſibly ſeen with thoſe eies,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Heb.</hi> 11.27.</note> by which we doe ſee him, either in Grace or Glory.</p>
            <p>
               <label>Nayler.</label> Yet <hi>Nayler</hi> ſtill perſiſted in his confidence, that ſome thing might be ſeen inviſibly, and continued his railing and reviling phraſes, liars, liars, or to that effect. <label>
                  <hi>4</hi> Queſtion Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſputed.</label> The time was farre ſpent; and Mr <hi>Bourn</hi> called to another Queſtion, and that was taken, which was the laſt that was propoſed, and the laſt that was diſputed. This was, whether it bee lawfull to call any man Maſter or Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther upon earth?</p>
            <p>The ſenſe and meaning of the Queſtion, was, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther it be lawfull to give any honour, or titles of ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour to men, to Father or Maſter, to Magiſtrate or Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter, to Lords or Ladies, or the like.</p>
            <p>The occaſion was in part, the Qakers crying out againſt the Miniſters of Chriſt, becauſe they are called of men Maſters; and in part the proud uncivill unchriſtian be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haviour of ſome Quakers towards their naturall pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents,
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:62479:21"/>and ordinary maſters; ſome towards civill Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrates, honourable Judges and Juſtices of peace, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore whom being called, they have (ſome of them in my ſight) kept on their hats in a contemptuous man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, and denied any outward honour, or civill reſpect to be given unto them; <label>Iames Nayler in his anſwer to this Queſtion, in his falſe Rela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</label> yea <hi>Nayler</hi> himſelfe in his writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten Anſwer, calleth us the Miniſters of Chriſt Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſt, becauſe we are called of men Maſters.</p>
            <p>And <hi>Richard Farnworth</hi> another rayling Quaker,<note place="margin">R. Farnworths diſcovery of Faith, and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers papers, page <hi>2.3.</hi>
               </note> and their common practice of refuſing to give any out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward reſpect to Magiſtrates, not only <hi>Fox</hi> and <hi>Nayler,</hi> but their ſeduced proſelytes witneſſe daily.</p>
            <p>But Mr <hi>Bourne</hi> brought an Argument, to prove it lawful to call or be called Maſter or Father, and to give civill honour, and titles of honour, and reſpect to men, according to their place and dignity, to this effect.</p>
            <p>
               <label>Mr Bournes Argument.</label> Whatſoever titles of honour, or reſpect the holy Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>triarchs or Prophets, or Apoſtles, or other faithfull men have given unto or received from each other, which are no where forbidden in the Scripture, or written word of God, thoſe are lawfull for Chriſtians, now to give unto, or to receive from each other. But theſe titles of honour or reſpect, as Father and Maſter, and Lord and Lady, and the like, they have been given and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived by the Patriarchs and Prophets, &amp; Apoſtles, and other holy faithfull men, and are no where forbidden in the Scripture or written word of God. Therefore the ſame titles or names of Father and Maſter, Lord and Lady, and the like may lawfully be given and received by Chriſtians in theſe daies, or in this age of the world. Firſt propoſition I conceive will not be denyed, except by ſuch as will not be tried by the holy Scriptures. And for the minor or ſecond propoſition, we ſhall make that evident by an induction from ſingular or particular ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amples of godly men recorded in holy writ.</p>
            <p>Firſt, if you read <hi>Gen.</hi> 23.6. You may finde, <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Example. </seg>1</label> that when <hi>Abraham</hi> came to the children of <hi>Heth</hi> to ge<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> a burying place for <hi>Sarah</hi> his wife (ſhee being then
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:62479:22"/>dead) hee ſpake to the children of <hi>Heth,</hi> and bowed downe himſelfe to the people of the land, to give un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to them, not any divine religious worſhip, which is due to God, but civill honour due to men; and three times is <hi>Abraham</hi> there called Lord by that people, and faithfull <hi>Abraham</hi> taketh that title to himſelfe, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any reproofe of them, for giving that title to him, or any refuſing of that title given him, which he would not have done, if it had not been lawfull to have re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived any ſuch honour, nor would he have bowed downe himſelfe to the people of the land, if it had been ſinne to have done ſo. For <hi>Abraham</hi> was a knowing faithfull man, believing in Chriſt the Meſſiah to come, and rejoicing to ſee Chriſts day, witneſſe our Saviour, <hi>John</hi> 8.
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iohn</hi> 8.56.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note>
            </p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> Againe, read <hi>Gen.</hi> 24. When <hi>Abraham</hi> ſent his re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligious ſervant to provide a wife for his ſonne <hi>Iſaac,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Gen.</hi> 24.27:</note> his ſervant putteth up his prayer to God, O Lord God of my Maſter <hi>Abraham,</hi> ſend me good ſpeed this day, and ſhew kindneſſe to my Maſter <hi>Abraham.</hi> And hee calleth <hi>Abraham</hi> Maſter, ſixteen or ſeventeen times in that Chapter, which certainly he would not have done, if it had not been lawfull to call Maſter.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> Thirdly,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Gen.</hi> 32.18.</note> read <hi>Gen.</hi> 32. And you may finde that <hi>Jacob</hi> calleth his brother <hi>Eſau,</hi> Lord, in that direction of his to his ſervants, whom he ſent before with a gift to his brother. When you meet my brother <hi>Eſau</hi> (ſaith he) and he ſhall aske you, whoſe are theſe Cattell? you ſhall anſwer, it is a preſent ſent to my Lord <hi>Eſau;</hi> and he cals <hi>Eſau</hi> Lord foure times in that Chapter.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> Fourthly,
<note place="margin">1 <hi>Kin,</hi> 18.7, 8.</note> read 1 <hi>Kin.</hi> 18. When religious <hi>Obadiah</hi> (who did feare the Lord from his youth) met <hi>Elijah</hi> the Prophet; he calleth <hi>Elijah</hi> Lord. Art not thou my Lord <hi>Elijah.</hi> And verſe the 8. The Prophet calleth wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked <hi>Ahab Obadiahs</hi> Lord: For thus ſpeaketh hee to <hi>Obadiah,</hi> Go tell thy Lord, behold, <hi>Elijah</hi> is here. Thus doth that good Prophet, not only ſuffer himſelfe to bee called Lord, but calleth wicked King <hi>Ahab Obadiahs</hi>
               <pb n="33" facs="tcp:62479:22" rendition="simple:additions"/>Lord, which he would not have done, if it had not been lawfull; and if it were lawfull to call prophane <hi>Eſau</hi> Lord, and wicked <hi>Ahab</hi> Lord? wherefore is it not law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full to call Maſter or Father, or to give honourable ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tles to men now, unto whom they doe belong, both by naturall and civill reſpects, witneſſed by the practice of the Saints &amp; holy men in ſeveral ages of the world?</p>
            <p>For, fifthly, if you read 2 <hi>Kin.</hi> 2. Did not the chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren of the Prophets at <hi>Bethel,</hi> call <hi>Elijah, Eliſhas</hi> Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter? Knoweſt thou not that the Lord will take away thy Maſter from thy head to day? And againe, another company of the Prophets at <hi>Jericho?</hi> verſe 5. Knoweſt thou not that the Lord will take away thy Maſter from thy head to day? And in the ſame Chapter, verſe 12. When <hi>Elijah</hi> was taken up into heaven in a fiery Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riot, <hi>Eliſha</hi> cryeth out, my Father my, Father, the Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riot of Iſrael, and the horſemen thereof. Thus you ſee, titles of honour, Lord, Maſter, Father, are both given and received by holy men, and this without any re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proofe or check of the Spirit of God, recorded in the Scriptures, concerning any of theſe examples, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ſure it was and is lawfull, to give and receive ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tles of reſpect and honour, to call or be called Lord or Maſter, or Father, according to every ones place and dignity. All theſe places of Scripture were not then alledged.</p>
            <p>
               <label>Naylers Anſwer.</label> And <hi>James Nayler</hi> by his loud clamour, hindred the preſſing and application of thoſe places that were al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledged (as much as he could) and cried out, that was in the Law, but now in the Goſpell, Chriſt forbids to call any man Maſter, or to be called of men Maſters or Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and alledged that of our Saviour, <hi>Mat.</hi> 23. But be not ye called Rabbi, for one is your Maſter, even Chriſt, and all ye are brethren; and call no man your Father upon earth, for one is your Father<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> which is in heaven. And hence <hi>Nayler</hi> would infer, That now in time of the Goſpell, it was not lawfull tocall any man Maſter, or to be called of men Maſter or Father, upon earth.</p>
            <pb n="34" facs="tcp:62479:23"/>
            <p>
               <label>Mr Bournes. Reply.</label> Then I replied, and bad <hi>Nayler</hi> read the context in the verſes before, and if his eies were open, he might ſee the mind of Chriſt, that it was not abſolutely to for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bid his hearers to call any man Maſter or Father, but to forbid the ambitious ſeeking of honor, and the ambi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious love of honour, which was in the Scribes and Phariſees. This you may finde is that that he reproveth in them, in the 6 and 7 verfes. They love (ſaith Chriſt) the uppermoſt rooms at Feaſts, and the chiefe ſeats in the Synagogues, and greetings in the Markets, and to be called of men, Rabbi, Rabbi: And this ambitious pride and love of honour from men, Chriſt reproveth in the Phariſees; and this he forbiddeth his diſciples, but be not ye called Rabbi, for one is your Maſter, even Chriſt, and all ye are brethren, he would not have his Apoſtles to ſeeke ſuperiority and power one over ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in a proud ambitious manner, <hi>Diotrephes</hi>-like to love to have the preheminence, as 3 <hi>John</hi> 9. the Evan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geliſt doth witneſle <hi>Diotrephes</hi> did. Yet our Saviour Chriſt here doth not ſimply and abſolutely forbid all giving or receiving of honour, or of calling, or being called of men Maſter, or Father, or Lord or Lady, or the like. Yet it is certaine, our Saviour Chriſt doth forbid ſo to call Maſter or Father, as to make any man the Maſter or Father of our Faith, inſtead of Chriſt; or that any man ſhould be called Maſter or Father, ſo as to take the honour of chiefe Maſter or Father, or Teacher, to him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, which is due to Chriſt. This is that which Chriſt forbiddeth; and this is that which the Apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi> for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>biddeth the <hi>Corinthians,</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1. Now this I ſay (ſaith the Apoſtle) that every one of you ſaith, I am of <hi>Paul,</hi> and I of <hi>Apollo,</hi> and I of <hi>Cephas,</hi> and I of Chriſt. One ſaid he was <hi>Pauls</hi> Diſciple; another, he was <hi>Apollos;</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother, he was Chriſts. But what ſaith the Apoſtle, is Chriſt divided? was <hi>Paul</hi> crucified for you? Thus they made <hi>Paul</hi> the Maſter or Father of their faith. And this the Apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi> reproveth here. And this Chriſt our Saviour reproveth and forbiddeth, <hi>Mat.</hi> 23. And
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:62479:23" rendition="simple:additions"/>Chriſt doth forbid to give that divine honour which is due to God and Chriſt, that God-man our Saviour, to any man in the world; but hee doth not forbid to give or receive civill honour and reſpect one to another, according to each mans place and dignity, or ſo to be called of men, Maſter or Father, or the like.</p>
            <p>To this effect was the Anſwer given, but more cloſe and briefe then now I give it.</p>
            <p>But <hi>Nayler,</hi> inſtead of any better Anſwer, cried out, lyar, lyar, hold thy peace for ſhame, doth not Chriſt plainly forbid to call Father or Maſter, and made a great clamorous noiſe, and bid, ſi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> downe for ſhame, for ſhame.</p>
            <p>
               <label>Mr Bourns Reply.</label> Then Mr <hi>Bourn</hi> called to <hi>Nayler,</hi> and bid him leave his loud ſhameleſſe out cries, and hearken to an Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to prove the Expoſition to be truth, and accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the mind of Chriſt, which was to this ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Argument. </seg>2</label> Whatſoever Chriſt himſelfe, or the Spirit of Chriſt in the Apoſtles of Chriſt, doth approve of elſewhere in thenew Teſtament, as lawfull to be done, that Chriſt himſelfe doth not forbid in that place, <hi>Mat.</hi> 23. But Chriſt himſelfe, and the Spirit of Chriſt in the Apoſtles, doth elſewhere approve of the calling of men Maſters, and Fathers, and of giving other titles of reſpect and honour to men: Therefore Chriſt in that place, <hi>Mat.</hi> 23. did not forbid to call any man Maſter or Father, as <hi>James Nayler</hi> pretendeth. The firſt propoſition is wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſed to be clear, becauſe Chriſt is truth, yea, the way, the truth, and the life, and he is no way contrary to himſelfe. For Jeſus Chriſt is yeſterday, and to day, and the ſame for ever, <hi>Heb.</hi> 13. Therefore Chriſt doth not forbid that here, <hi>Mat.</hi> 23. which he alloweth elſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>where. And for the ſecond propoſition, that Chriſt and his ſpirit in the Apoſtles, doth approve and allow fit titles of honour to bee given to men, as is agreeable to their conditions in their ſeverall places. This will bee evident, &amp; if you read rightly conſider, that of the Evan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geliſt,
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:62479:24" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <hi>Marke</hi> 7. Where Chriſt is witneſſed to repeat the Commandement, Honour thy Father and thy Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther; and in the next verſe, Chriſt himſelfe giveth the name of Father and Mother to the parents of the man, of whom he ſpake to the Phariſees. And (ſaith Chriſt) ye ſuffer him no more to do ought for his Father and Mother. Now Chriſt certainly would not have named Father and Mother, nor have approved of thoſe titles and that relation, if it had not been lawfull. And the ſame alſo doth the Spirit of Chriſt in the Apoſtle <hi>Paul,</hi> in divers places, read <hi>Eph.</hi> 6. <hi>Col.</hi> 3. <hi>Col.</hi> 4. and you may finde, he giveth the titles of Father and Maſter. Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour thy father and mother, and fathers provoke not your children, and maſters give unto your ſervants that which is juſt and equall, knowing that ye alſo have a maſter in heaven. And the Apoſtle <hi>Peter</hi> to the ſame effect, 1 <hi>Pet</hi> 2. Honour all men, love the brother-hood, feare God, honour the King (the ſupreme magiſtrate by whatſoever title he be called) And ſervants be ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject to your maſters with all feare, not only to the good and gentle, but alſo to the froward; ſo that here are earthly fathers and maſters, as well as God and Chriſt is our father and maſter in heaven. And therefore it is evident, that our Saviour Chriſt in that place, <hi>Mat.</hi> 23. did not ſimply and abſolutely forbid to call or to bee called maſter or father; for if he had, he would not have approved it himſelfe, nor would the Apoſtles of Chriſt (who had the Spirit of Chriſt) have done it, as we have proved they did; to this purpoſe was the Argument, but ſhorter.</p>
            <p>
               <label>Naylers Anſwer.</label> Then <hi>Nayler</hi> was conſtrained to acknowledge, that a naturall father might bee called father by his child, and a civill maſter might bee called maſter by his ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vant; but that it was not lawfull for any other to give or receive ſuch honour, or titles of honour, as father or maſter, or the like, or to that effect. Although this ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledgement of <hi>Naylers</hi> was contrary to the Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine and practice even of <hi>Nayler</hi> himſelfe, and divers
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:62479:24" rendition="simple:additions"/>of his fellow Quakers and proſelytes, as the uncivill carriage of ſome of them towards their naturall pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents, and civill maſters, and of others towards Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrates and Miniſters, doth witneſſe at full.
<note place="margin">Mr Gardiner Miniſter of Eckinton.</note> Mr <hi>Gur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diner</hi> (a good Diſputant) as I remember, ſeeing <hi>Nayler</hi> wrangle, and endeavour to ſhift off from the Queſtion, began to preſſe <hi>Nayler</hi> with an Argument. But before Mr <hi>Gardiner</hi> could ſpeake out his Argument, <label>Naylers Reply.</label> 
               <hi>Nayler</hi> would not heare him, but he and ſome other of his ſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low Quakers that ſtood by him, cried out aloud, lyar, lyar, ſtop thy mouth, and made a clamouring noiſe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt him, to cauſe him to hold his peace. <label>Mr Gardiner.</label> To whom Mr <hi>Gardiner</hi> ſeeing <hi>Nayler</hi>'s ſo uncivill, unchriſtian, and unreaſonable behaviour; Replied, fie on thee thou unreaſonable man, thou art not fit to be reaſoned with, or to that purpoſe, and ſo turned his backe upon him.</p>
            <p>
               <label>Mr Bournes Argument.</label> Then Mr <hi>Bourne</hi> called aloud to <hi>Nayler</hi> againe, and bad him leave his uncivill rayling and reviling ſpeeches, and loud clamours, and hearken to an Argument to prove it, which was to this effect.</p>
            <p>That title of honour which St <hi>Paul</hi> did give to <hi>Fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtus,</hi> who was none of his naturall father, nor civill maſter, that it is lawfull for Chriſtians, to give now to thoſe who are neither naturall fathers, nor ordinary ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vill maſters. But read <hi>Acts</hi> 26. and you may finde, that St <hi>Paul</hi> ſtiled <hi>Festus,</hi> noble <hi>Feſtus,</hi> which is a title of honour, and high reſpect, and therefore it is lawfull now to give honourable titles, to ſuch as are neither naturall parents, nor civill maſters, and to be given by ſuch as are neither naturall children, nor meniall or hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red ſervants or to this end was the Argument.</p>
            <p>
               <label>Naylers Anſwer.</label> 
               <hi>Nayler</hi> anſwered thoſe were noble Romans, and deſerved honour, &amp;c. But now, &amp;c. as if he thought now we had none ſo worthy, to whom ſuch honour ſhould be given (for to my beſt obſervation, this was the ſence of his broken ſpeech) for hee did not ſpeake whole ſentences, but wrangled about giving honour, and ſaid, howſoever honour might be given to naturall
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:62479:25"/>parents, or civill maſters, yet how could we prove, that any that profeſſed themſelves Miniſters of Chriſt, ſhould be called maſter or father, contrary to that of Chriſt, <hi>Mat.</hi> 23. noted before, where he ſaid, Chriſt did par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticularly forbid his Apoſtles and miniſters, to be ſo cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led.</p>
            <p>
               <label>Mr Bournes Reply.</label> To which Mr <hi>Bourne</hi> replied, <hi>Nayler,</hi> and bad him reade again that place, <hi>Mat.</hi> 23.1, 2. and thou ſhalt find, that Chriſt did ſpeake there to the multitude, as well as to his Diſciples, and what in that text he did not forbid others, he did not forbid them. Conſider the Text fully, and thou maieſt ſee it plaine, if thou haſt eies to ſee.</p>
            <p>
               <label>Naylers Anſwer</label> 
               <hi>Nayler</hi> according to his cuſtome, inſtead of other Anſwers, cried out, it is falſe, it is falſe, prove that any Miniſter of Chriſt ſhould be called maſter or father, or have any ſuch honour given to them or to that effect.</p>
            <p>
               <label>Mr Maudeſley</label> Mr <hi>Maudesly</hi> Miniſter of <hi>Dronfield,</hi> being neer to <hi>Nayler</hi> (as I remember) brought an Argument from that place, <hi>Eccl.</hi> 12.11. The words of the wiſe are like goads faſtened by the maſters of the Aſſemblies. And if by the Maſters of the Aſſemblies be intended teach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers of Gods people, and Miniſters of Chriſt, then it is lawfull for them to be called maſters, becauſe the Spirit of God in <hi>Solomon,</hi> calleth them ſo. But this is apparent, that by maſters he meaneth teachers, therefore it is lawfull to call the miniſters of Chriſt who are teachers, of Gods people, maſters, or to that purpoſe.</p>
            <p>
               <label>Naylers Anſwer</label> But <hi>James Nayler</hi> ſings ſtill his old ſong, liar, liar, no ſuch thing is intended there, and wrangled igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rantly about the ſence of that place, as nothing concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning miniſters in the New Teſtament.</p>
            <p>
               <label>Mr Bournes Argument.</label> Then <hi>Mr Bourne</hi> bad <hi>Nayler</hi> to heare an Argument out of the New Teſtament, from that place of the Apoſtle to <hi>Timothy,</hi> 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 5.17. Let the Elders that rule well, be accounted worthy of double honour, eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially them that labour in the word and doctrine to this effect. If preaching Elders that labour in the word and
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:62479:25"/>doctrine be worthy of double honour, then the faithfull labouring miniſters of Chriſt, are worthy of honour; but preaching Elders who labour in the word and do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine, are worthy of double honour, witneſſe the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle in that place, 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 5. therefore the miniſters of Chriſt, who labour in the word and doctrine, are wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy of honour, and ſo may lawfully have honour given them; yea, that honour which is due to them, that is, not only the honour of maintenance, but the honour of reverence and eſteem; let a man eſteem of us as mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters of Chriſt, and ſtewards of the myſteries of God, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 4.12.</p>
            <p>
               <label>Nailers Anſwer</label> This was not ſo fully preſſed then. But <hi>Nayler</hi> an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered and ſaid, The miniſters of Chriſt they muſt bee honoured in the Lord, but not be called maſter or fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and have any outward honour. And ſtill <hi>Nayler</hi> wrangled, and turned to thoſe people neer him, not an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwering the Argument, but railed at miniſters for ſuffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring our ſelves to be called maſters, vapouring in con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temptuous termes, but bringing no word of proofe at all.</p>
            <p>
               <label>Mr Bournes Argument.</label> 
               <hi>Mr Bourne</hi> bad <hi>Nayler</hi> leave off his vapouring, or to that effect, and hearken to another Scripture, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 4.15. where St <hi>Paul</hi> did take to himſelfe the name of father of the Corinthians, their ſpirituall father, though you have ten thouſand inſtructers (ſaith he) yet yee have not many fathers, for in Chriſt Jeſus I have be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gotten you through the Goſpell. Now if <hi>Paul</hi> as a mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter of Chriſt converting ſoules, did lawfully take to himſelf, the name of father; Then the faithfull miniſters of Chriſt who convert men and women to Chriſt, may lawfully take to themſelves the name of father; but this was lawfull for bleſſed <hi>Paul,</hi> therefore it is lawfull alſo for all the faithfull miniſters of Chriſt Jeſus, who turne men to God, to take to themſelves the name of father and ſo to be called maſters or ſirs, which is a title of honour and reſpect: For what title was lawfull to that bleſſed Apoſtle, and <hi>Silas,</hi> preachers of the Goſpel,
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:62479:26"/>to receive from men, and they did accept that as law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full now to Gods faithfull miniſters: But it was lawfull for the Apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi> and <hi>Silas,</hi> to receive the title of ſirs or maſters,
<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>Domini, Sirs or Maſters, a title of honour.</hi>
               </note> and they did accept of that title of ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour from the Jayler, <hi>Acts</hi> 16. He came trembling, and fell downe before <hi>Paul</hi> and <hi>Silas,</hi> and ſaid, Sirs, or Lords or maſters. what muſt I do to be ſaved? there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore it is lawfull for the miniſters of Chriſt, now to be called ſirs or maſters, and to receive ſuch titles or re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpects, which are due to their miniſteriall place, and honourable calling. The Argument was not then ſo fully and largely given, but to this effect <hi>Mr Bourn</hi> was preſſing to prove this truth, But <hi>James Nayler</hi> like the deafe Adder, turned away his eare, and would not an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer, and according to his practice, when he was not able to anſwer an argument,
<note place="margin">Mr Bourn and Mr Billingsley ſtood in the reading ſeat, and James Nayler was in a ſeat neer Mr Major, a good diſtance from the reading ſeate.</note> looked aſide, and ſpake at randome to the people, in a bragging vapouring man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, what he could doe; and while we were preſſing him to anſwer, we did ſee <hi>Mr Major,</hi> and ſome other nere him, going forth of their ſeats, and <hi>Nayler</hi> and others following, and ſo the Diſputation ended ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruptly.</p>
            <p>But if any underſtanding Chriſtian, who is not by<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aſſed by miſinformation of his judgement, conſider theſe Arguments, they are ſufficient to prove that ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nourable reſpect that is due to the miniſters of Chriſt, not that Chriſts miniſters ſhould ambitiouſly ſeeke after honours or honourable titles, for that Chriſt for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bids, and that Gods faithfull Embaſſadours affect not, endeavour not. But yet when falſe teachers ſeeke to diſgrace, and prophane perſons with their wicked plots and deſignes to diſhonour us, and our honourable miniſteriall calling, we are bound in conſcience with St <hi>Paul,</hi> to magnifie our office, and to vindicate our ſelves from ſuch wicked practiſes of erring Quakers, and of prophane ungodly malicious men, who neglect and contemne the Ordinances of Jeſus Chriſt. Thus, as neer as I can remember, out of my notes taken, and
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:62479:26" rendition="simple:additions"/>what I could learn of others, I have given a juſt and true relation of that Diſpute at <hi>Cheſterfield,</hi> if it were worthy of that name, being a wrangling by that man, who had not artificiallie, ſcarce naturall order of rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoning, but like a boiſterous railing fellow, who by loud out-cries, little or nothing to the purpoſe, ſought to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive the people. A witty honeſt Gentleman who was preſent at the Diſpute, asked his name, and one told him his name was <hi>James Nayler;</hi> to whom (as I was informed) he replyed, certainly his name ſhould no more be called <hi>James Nayler,</hi> but <hi>James</hi> Rayler; for (ſaid he) I never heard a more bawling, railing, revi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling fellow talke; or words to that purpoſe. The Lord give him repentance, if it be his will. I have ſaid ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent to the Queſtion, to prove the lawfulneſſe of giving honour to Chriſts Miniſters.
<note place="margin">That it is law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full to give ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour.</note> Now I ſhall only add a few Arguments to prove the lawfulneſſe, yea, duty, of giving outward honour, as well as inward honour to Magiſtrates and others, according to their place and dignity, whatſoever theſe Quakers gatrulate to the contrary. It is lawfull to give the title of Lord and Lady, and the like, and to declare our due reſpect by outward teſtimonies of the honour and due regard we doe owe unto them as to ſuperiours. <label>Iames Nuyler.</label> It is true, <hi>James Nayler</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing examined upon an indictment of blaſphemy a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt him, at the Seſſions at <hi>Appleby,</hi> in <hi>January.</hi> 1652.<note place="margin">See the briefe reply to ſome part of a ſcur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rilous and lying pamphlet, called Sauls errand to Damaſcus, printed <hi>1653.</hi>
               </note> kept on his hat before the Bench; and when Juſtice <hi>Pearſon,</hi> one of the Juſtices, commanded to put off their hats, <hi>James Nayler</hi> anſwered, I doe it not in con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt of authority. And he being asked againe by Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lonell <hi>Briggs,</hi> If hee were in the Parliament Houſe, wouldeſt thou keep it on? To whom <hi>James</hi> anſwered, if God ſhould keep me in the ſame mind I am now in, I ſhould. Then Colonell <hi>Briggs</hi> replied, I knew thou wouldeſt contemne authority. The ſame hath been the practice of divers other of the ſeduced, ſeducing Qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kers, before the honourable Juſtices of the Peace in ſeverall Countries. And <hi>Naylers</hi> pretence of giving
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:62479:27"/>honour inwardly, when they refuſe to give any out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward civill reſpect, what is it but phariſaicall diſſimu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation, inſtead of ſincere humility and obedience, or duty to thoſe whom the Lord hath ſet over us in pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er and authority, for his glory, and the good of his peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple: For ſhall we not judge the tree by its fruits? But let me evidence duty a little in this reſpect.</p>
            <p n="1">
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Argument. </seg>1</label> 1. Thoſe who by Gods Ordinance are ſet in place above others in Gods ſtead, for the peoples good, they are to have honour given to them above others, to be declared outwardly, as well as ſetled inwardly in the hearts of men.</p>
            <p>But Magiſtrates ſupreme and inferiour, Judges and Juſtices, and ſuch as are of higher or lower place and power, they are by Gods Ordinance, ſet in place above others in Gods ſtead for the peoples good: Therefore they are to have honor given unto them above others, to be declared outwardly, as well as ſetled inwardly in the hearts of men. The major or firſt propoſition, is moſt agreeable to reaſon and order even in nature it ſelfe. The herbes and graſſe of the field, which are infe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riour, and have but a vegetive life, they doe ſervice, and give a kind of obedience in Gods Ordinance, for the nouriſhment and ſervice of the beaſts and cattell, which are ſuperiour in nature, and have beſides a vege<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive or growing life, a life of ſence alſo, which is more excellent. Againe, theſe brute creatures which have only the vegetive and ſenſitive life, they are infe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riour unto, and doe ſervice, and yield obedience unto man, which is a more noble creature, ſuperiour to the other, as having not only a vegetive and ſenſitive, but alſo a rationall life, and more excelling inferiour crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures; and man hath yet the great God, and Creator of heaven and earth, above him, to whom he doth owe honour and ſervice both in ſoule and body, <hi>Rom.</hi> 12.1. Thus in order of nature, and thus in order of govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, the Comm-wealths and governments of Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, there is and ought to be order of ſuperiour and
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:62479:27" rendition="simple:additions"/>inferiour;
<note place="margin">1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 14.33.</note> for as in the Churches of the Saints (ſo in Common-wealths) God is not the Author of Confu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, but of peace and good order in all; And ſo an orderly reſpect is to be had to every ſuperiour, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to their place and power. The Apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi> giveth evidence to this at full, <hi>Rom.</hi> 13.1, &amp;c. Let every ſoule be ſubject unto the higher powers, for there is no pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er but of God, and the powers that be ordained of God, they are Gods Ordinance, and hee is the Miniſter of God to thee for good. For this cauſe pay you tribute alſo, for they are Gods miniſters attending continually upon this very thing; And hence he concludes, render therefore to all their dues, tribute to whom tribute, cuſtome to whom cuſtome, feare to whom feare, ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour to whom honour. Thus honour is a due as well as tribute or cuſtome, or any other ſervice. I might call in the Apoſtle <hi>Peter</hi> to witneſs the ſame, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.13, 14, 17. but I refer the Reader to the Scripture it ſelf, theſe teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie an honor due to our ſuperiours. And for the minor or ſecond propoſition; That magiſtrates ſupreme or infe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riour, are Gods Ordinance ſet and approved by God for government above others; the places alledged might ſuffice, but if you read <hi>Exod.</hi> 18.21, 23. when <hi>Jethro, Moſes</hi> Father in law, gave him that good counſell, to provide out of all the people able men, ſuch as feare God, men of truth, hating covetouſneſſe, and to place them over them to be Rulers of thouſands, of hundreds, of fifties, and of tens. And if thou doe this thing, and God command thee ſo, then ſhalt thou be able to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dure, and this people ſhall goe to their place in peace. And <hi>Moſes</hi> did ſo, and God himſelfe doth approve of this order of government, of ſuperiours and inferiours, and giveth <hi>Moſes</hi> order to gather to God ſeventy El<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders, and the Lord taketh of the Spirit of government, that was upon <hi>Moſes,</hi> and gave it to the ſeventy El<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders, as you may read <hi>Numb.</hi> 11.16, 17, 25. Thus are Governours over the people, of Gods owne ordination, as ſuperiours, and ſo a higher honour and reſpect is due unto them.</p>
            <pb n="44" facs="tcp:62479:28" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Argument. </seg>2</label> Againe, that outward manifeſtation of honour, and thoſe titles of honour, which have been given by holy men in Scripture, to Princes, Magiſtrates and Judges, and others according to their places and dignities, which are not reproved by Gods Spirit, that may law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully bee given now to Princes, to Judges, Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrates, Governours and others, according to their pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces and dignities. But outward manifeſtation of honour and honourable titles, have been given by holy men in Scripture, to Princes, Judges and Magiſtrates, and others, according to their place and dignities, therefore they may be given now to ſuch without ſinne; yea, it is our duties ſo to doe.
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 82.16.</note> Doth not the Scripture call them Gods as in Gods ſtead? And to evidence both propoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Example. </seg>1</label> I ſhall give you ſeverall examples. If we read that place; <hi>Numb.</hi> 11.28. when the Spirit of God reſted upon <hi>Eldad</hi> and <hi>Medad</hi> in the campe, <hi>Joſhua</hi> in his zeale ſpeaks to <hi>Moſes</hi> to forbid them, and cals him Lord, and <hi>Joſhua</hi> ſaid, my Lord <hi>Moſes</hi> forbid them; he giveth him an honourable title, my Lord <hi>Moſes.</hi> And did not wiſe <hi>Abigal</hi> call <hi>David</hi> Lord, when he was comming with his Souldiers to deſtroy churliſh <hi>Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bal</hi> for his ingratitude? 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 25 24, 25, &amp;c. Yea di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers times in that Chapter, ſhe giveth <hi>David</hi> the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nourable title of Lord. And did not good <hi>David</hi> cry after King <hi>Saul,</hi> and giveth him this honourable title, my Lord the King? 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 24.8. And doth he not then give outward reverence to <hi>Saul,</hi> to witneſſe his hono<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable reſpects to <hi>Saul,</hi> as to his ſuperiour in place and power; the text ſaith, <hi>David</hi> ſtooped with his face to the earth, and bowed himſelfe? This is far unlike <hi>Naylers</hi> and his quaking companions carriage, even to Princes, Magiſtrates, and Judges, and Juſtices of the peace, to ſtand with their hats on their heads, and to ſpeak to them in an irreverent manner; thou man, or thee man, who ſitteſt in the place of judgement, do this or that, as ſome of them have ſaid and done. May I not ſay the ſame of <hi>Abner,</hi> who (as <hi>David</hi> teſtifieth) was a Prince,
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:62479:28" rendition="simple:additions"/>and a great man in Iſrael, yet when he came to <hi>David,</hi> he gave him titles of honour; I will goe ſaith he, and gather all Iſrael unto my Lord the King, 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 3.21. What need I tell you of that great Prophet of God, <hi>Elijah,</hi> doth he not call <hi>Ahab Obadiahs</hi> Lord, goe tell thy Lord, behold <hi>Elijah</hi> is here, 1 <hi>Kin.</hi> 18.14. Though <hi>Ahab</hi> was a wicked man, yet hee doth not take from him his title of honour. And doth not the Spirit of God give the title of Lord to that noble man, on whoſe hand the King leaned? 2 <hi>Kin.</hi> 7.2. What need I tell you, that in the New Teſtament, the bleſſed Evangeliſt <hi>Luke,</hi> in that his hiſtory of the Goſpell which he did write to <hi>Theophilus,</hi> he giveth him that honourable title, moſt excellent <hi>Theophilus, Luke</hi> 1.3. a title of great honour and high eſteem given to <hi>Theophilus;</hi> And bleſſed <hi>Paul</hi> calleth <hi>Feſtus</hi> the Governour of that Province, noble <hi>Festus, Acts</hi> 26.25, 27. And in the ſame Chapter, when he was before King <hi>Agrippa,</hi> to anſwer for himſelfe, he doth not in a proud or blind ignorant ſottiſh man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, call <hi>Agrippa</hi> thou man, or thee man (as the Quakers doe) but King <hi>Agrippa,</hi> believeſt thou the Prophets, I know that thou believeſt. Thus do theſe Saints give ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tles of honour according to mens place and dignities; I will name but one more, and that is the bleſſed Evan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geliſt St <hi>John,</hi> that beloved Diſciple of Chriſt <hi>John</hi> 19.26. in his ſecond Epiſtle, hee giveth that gratious woman, to whom he writ her title of honour and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect, verſe 1. The Elder (ſaith he) to the elect Lady; And againe verſe 5. I beſeech thee Lady, Thus doth the bleſſed Apoſtle, give titles of honour, to whom honour belongs. And theſe certainly, are witneſſes ſufficient to juſtifie this truth againſt the Quakers; that there may be ſome kinde of reſpect, civill reſpect I mean, though not to corrupt or flatter, yet to know and owne diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence of perſons, and to give to each that honor which is due to them in their ſeverall places.</p>
            <p>Againe, as it is a duty to give honour and reſpect, ſo it is lawfull for Princes, Judges, Juſtices and others, to
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:62479:29" rendition="simple:additions"/>this honour, when in a right and due manner it is given unto them. I ſhall call in only one witneſſe to evidence this truth, beſides thoſe whom I named before, to whom honor was given of men, none of w<hi rend="sup">ch</hi> godly men did re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject that honor which was aſcribed &amp; given unto them which had it been unlawfull to have received, they would certainly have refuſed. The witneſſe is that holy man <hi>Job,</hi> one that feared God, and eſchewed evill, and what doth he teſtifie of himſelfe? you may read, <hi>Job</hi> 29.7, 8, &amp;c. when I went out of the gate (ſaith he) through the City, when I prepare my ſeat in the ſtreet, the young men ſaw me, and hid themſelves, and the aged aroſe and ſtood up. Righteous <hi>Job</hi> was an honourable and juſt Judge, he was eies to the blind, and feet to the lame; he was a father to the poor, and the cauſe which he knew not, he ſearched it out; he did break the jawes of the wicked, and plucked the ſpoile out of his teeth, therefore was <hi>Job</hi> honourable, and both old and young did honor <hi>Job,</hi> not in their hearts only (as the Quakers would have magiſtrates honoured) but outwardly alſo, in giving all civill outward honour unto them, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to their ſeverall place and dignities; and good rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon it ſhould be ſo: For who more honourable, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fitable, and neceſſary, then good religious, juſt and righteous Judges and Magiſtrates, in a Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth? When juſtice is rightly executed, it exalteth a a Nation,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Prov.</hi> 14 34.</note> but ſinne is a ſhame to a people: The want of magiſtracy and government, prepareth a people for deſtruction,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iudges</hi> 18.7. <hi>My Text the</hi> 2d <hi>time I preached before the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nourable Iudges at Darby Aſſiſes, in which I pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved the neceſſity of, and honour due to Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrates, at full.</hi>
               </note> witneſſe that City <hi>Laiſh,</hi> who periſhed ſuddenly: And this is one reaſon given. There was no Magiſtrate in the Land, which might (puniſh, or) put them to ſhame in any thing. And this ſhall ſuffice to witneſſe againſt all adverſaries whatſoever, and cleare up and reſolve the Queſtion into this concluſion, That it is lawfull to call Maſter or Father, and to give honour to every one, even to the higheſt powers, and to infe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riour Magiſtrates, to the honourable Judges and Juſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, and to all others, according to their ſeverall places
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:62479:29" rendition="simple:additions"/>and dignities whatſoever; yet ſo as the honour and glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of God is to be exalted above all.</p>
            <p>And thus I have ended theſe foure Queſtions diſpu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted. There were three more Queſtions; but for theſe and <hi>Naylers</hi> anſwers, and his croſſe interrogatories, I have given my ſufficient anſwer before, and my reaſon wherefore I print no more, namely, becauſe they are ſo fully anſwered already by many learned divines, that it were but to caſt water into the ſea, as I have expreſſed in the one and twentieth page of this my Defence of the Scriptures, &amp;c. to which I refer the Reader.</p>
            <p>I ſhall only give ſome briefe Animadverſions upon <hi>Naylers</hi> moſt falſe relation of that Diſpute at <hi>Cheſter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>field,</hi> and paſſe to a concluſion.</p>
            <p n="1">1. It is an approved obſervation,
<note place="margin">Rectum eſt in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dex ſui &amp; ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liqui.</note> that a true and right rule will diſcover it ſelfe, and that which is falſe, and ſo will a true relation; therefore I need doe no more here, but refer the Reader to what I have before expreſſed; yet to draw the curtaine a little, that you may ſee <hi>Nay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers</hi> picture the better, I ſhall number up a number of his untruths, in that moſt falſe relation of that Diſpute.</p>
            <p n="1">
               <label>Naylers un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>truths.</label> 1. In the very title, <hi>Nayler</hi> calleth it a diſpute be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween <hi>James Nayler,</hi> and the pariſh-Teachers of <hi>Che<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterfield.</hi> This is an untruth, for there was but one of the Pariſh-Teachers of <hi>Cheſterfield,</hi> who had any hand in that Diſpute.</p>
            <p n="2">2. In the next line he addeth, By a challenge againſt him. This is a ſecond falſhood; for the challenge was on his ſide, not only by <hi>John Prith</hi> boaſting of <hi>Nayler,</hi> but by other of his fellow Quakers.</p>
            <p n="3">3. He ſaith, the ſimple may ſee the bloody minds of theſe men. This is a third untruth; for there were no bloody minds, nor thought of any perſecution againſt him, but of a Chriſtian Conference.</p>
            <p n="4">4. He ſaith, when we ſpeake faire, war is in our hearts. This is a fourth untruth, we had not war in our hearts, nor any deſires, but of peace, and that peace and rruth might dwell together.</p>
            <pb n="48" facs="tcp:62479:30" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p n="5">5. He ſaith, ſwearing and curſing, and blaſpheming the dreadfull name of God, are the fruits of <hi>John Bil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lingsley</hi>'s Miniſtry. This is a fifth untruth; for Mr <hi>Bil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ingsley</hi> never preached any ſuch doctrine, nor approved of any ſuch practice, nor did know of the Bul-baiting <hi>Nayler</hi> ſpake againſt. There was a poore man of <hi>Win<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerworth</hi> neer <hi>Cheſterfield,</hi> his name (as I was infor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med) was <hi>William Froſt;</hi> who having heard <hi>Naylers</hi> deſperate doctrine, and read ſome of his books, deſpai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, and went and drowned himſelfe: Was this the fruits of thy Miniſtry, <hi>Nayler?</hi> thou wilt not confeſſe it was.</p>
            <p n="6">6. <hi>Nayler</hi> cryeth out, and calleth Mr <hi>Billingsley</hi> man-pleaſer; O thou man-pleaſer (ſaith he.) This is a ſixt lie; for it is evident Mr <hi>Billingsley</hi> is not a man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleaſer, for he refuſeth to baptize children, except the parent will come unto him and be examined of the knowledge of his Faith. And doth not give the Lords Supper but to ſuch as he examineth and approveth, by which too many are diſpleaſed, which they would not, if they did know what was good for their owne ſoules.</p>
            <p n="7">7. (For I let paſſe divers) he ſaith God is riſen to cut us off, and it had been good we had never been borne. And I hope this is a ſeventh untruth, and a falſe prophecie. But <hi>Nayler</hi> manifeſteth his bloody mind, he would cut off all the faithful Miniſters of Chriſt if it were in his power. The Lord rebuke him.</p>
            <p n="8">8. Hee ſaith there was another plot againſt him. Which is an eighth untruth; there was not any plot, (as he pretended) as God and our conſcience can wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe for us.</p>
            <p n="9">9. For I omit againe divers abominable untruths obſerved by Mr <hi>Billingsley,</hi> in that part of <hi>Naylers</hi> falſe relation. <hi>Nayler</hi> againe ſaith, he was ſhewed the many plots laid, to have caſt him in priſon, and to proſecute our bloody intents. This is a 9<hi rend="sup">th</hi> untruth from the father of lies; if any ſhewed thee any ſuch thing, they were inventers, and thou art a publiſher of an abominable untruth.</p>
            <pb n="49" facs="tcp:62479:30" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p n="10">10. <hi>Nayler</hi> at the Diſputation, did moſt falſely ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſe me, that I did ſweare by <hi>Mary,</hi> when I did not ſo much as name <hi>Mary,</hi> as all that could heare me can witneſſe at full, nor did I ſweare at all; as in my letter I writ to him the next day, I juſtified ſully, and wiſhed him to repent his lying accuſation; which let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter he hath moſt falſely printed, heaping up one lye af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter another, in a moſt ſhameleſſe manner; as if the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit of lying and ſlander, had taken ful poſſeſſion of him, which I leave off to rehearſe, as being unwilling to blot my paper with ſo many of his odious ſtinking untruths; yet I ſhall mention one more moſt abominable. <hi>Nayler</hi> ſaith, page 10. That theſe Prieſts ſet themſelves with all their ſtrength, to prove ſwearing lawfull, &amp;c. which is a moſt helliſh lie. This was the truth, when <hi>Nayler</hi> wrangling, denied it to be lawfull to take any oath be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore a lawfull Magiſtrate, upon any occaſion, Mr <hi>Bil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lingsley</hi> proved it lawfull by divers places of Scripture, both out of the Old and New Teſtament, which <hi>Nayler</hi> baſely perverteth, and according to his cuſtome, raiſeth that moſt wicked ſlander, and here he fully maketh good that which is juſtified againſt him and his fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowes, in that briefe Relation of the irreligion of the Northerne Quakers, noted before, page 20. baſely to manifeſt themſelves notorious lyars; as in that Pamph<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>let called <hi>Sauls</hi> errand to <hi>Damaſcus,</hi> in which there are a hundred untruths, as may bee proved ſaith that Author, by a hundred witneſſes, and many of them ſaith he, will be as ready to ſay and unſay any thing, as if lying were a vertue; and that they make no conſcience of raiſing falſe reports againſt any that oppoſe them. And this I now finde to be moſt true in lying <hi>Nayler</hi> by this experience. But if the adverſaries of Chriſt called the Maſter of the houſe Belzeebub, no marvell if theſe Quaking adverſaries like the devil (that grand Quaker) do belye and ſcandalize the miniſters of Chriſt. The Lord forgive them if it be his will, if they have not ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned that ſinne unto death, of which St <hi>John</hi> witneſſeth.
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:62479:31" rendition="simple:additions"/>There is a ſinne unto death, I ſay not that thou ſhoul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſt pray for it, 1 <hi>John</hi> 5.16.</p>
            <p>Now for thy twenty Quaeries <hi>Nayler,</hi> which thou ſenteſt and addeſt towards the end; I have in part an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered them already in what I have writ, and part of them are ſuch Queſtions againſt which St <hi>Paul</hi> ſpeak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth, as tending not to edification of thoſe who are weak in the faith, <hi>Rom.</hi> 14.1, 2. but rather to their di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtraction, if not deſtruction, therefore more fit to be ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lenced and buried in darkneſſe, then to be revived or brought to light. Secondly, ſome are hypocriticall, like that of <hi>Herod</hi> to the wiſe men, <hi>Mat.</hi> 2.7, 8. Thirdly, ſome are curious Queſtions, to ſatisfie curious buſie minds, ſuch as thou art, which being anſwered, will not profit to godlineſſe or edification, contrary to the rule, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 14.26 Fourthly ſome of them are tempting cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious Queſtions, like thoſe of the Phariſees (thy Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers) to Chriſt our Saviour, which he either anſwereth by Queſtions to his adverſaries againe, or elſe wiſely rejects or avoids to eſcape their treacherous deſignes againſt him, as <hi>Mat.</hi> 21.23, 24, &amp;c. <hi>Mat.</hi> 22.16, 17, 18, &amp;c. Fifthly, ſome are fooliſh and unlearned Queſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, which gender ſtrifes, not love, or any benefit to ſoules, and which the Apoſtle directs <hi>Timothy</hi> to avoid, 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 2.23. and giveth the ſame command to <hi>Titus,</hi> becauſe ſaith he, they are unprofitable and vaine, <hi>Tit.</hi> 3.9. And I had rather follow St <hi>Pauls</hi> counſell, then ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfie thy folly. It is the counſell of the wiſe man, in ſome ſuch caſes to be ſilent, <hi>Prov.</hi> 26.4. Yet if thou wilt have an anſwer to thy twenty Quaeries, and to thy chal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lenge and brags, leſt thou be wiſe in thy own conceit, or any of thy generation, <hi>Prov.</hi> 26.5. know that all or moſt of them, or thoſe that are fit to be replyed unto, they are ſufficiently anſwered by divers religious learned men, Miniſters of the Goſpell, and others. If any deſire to ſee, Firſt let them read learned Mr <hi>Baxter</hi>'s anſwer to the ſixteen Quaeries,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>The Worceſter petition d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>fen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, printed</hi> 1653.</note> upon the <hi>Woſterſhire</hi> Petition; to which is added ſeventeen Counter-Quaeries, not yet anſwered
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:62479:31" rendition="simple:additions"/>by thee and thy fellowes that I have ſeen. 2. Read Mr <hi>Baxters</hi> Quakers Catechiſm,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>The Quakers confuted, prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted,</hi> 1654.</note> and the Quakers Queſtions anſwered there, printed 1655. 3. Read godly Mr <hi>Eaton,</hi> in his book called the Quakers confu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, being an anſwer to nineteen quaeries of thy com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panions, in which your weakneſſe and erroneous wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kedneſſe is diſcovered, and the truth vindicated. 4. Read that book called the Perfect Phariſee,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>The Perfect Phariſee, prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted</hi> 1654.</note> in which by way of poſition and proofe, your wandring quaeries are learnedly and religiously anſwered, by thoſe five godly Miniſters nere New Caſtle. 5.
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mr Fowler, &amp;c printed</hi> 1655.</note> Read ſolid and accute Mr <hi>Fowler</hi>'s book, called Satan at Noon Day, of the ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall ſorts of Quakers and Familiſts, And there you may ſee the matter of theſe familiſticall quaeries anſwered, and errors confuted to their ſorrow, if they had grace to be ſenſible. 6.
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>The myſtery of ungodlineſſe, printed</hi> 1653.</note> Read judicious and zealous Mr <hi>Far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer</hi> of <hi>Briſtol,</hi> in his book entituled the Myſtery of Godlineſſe and ungodlineſſe, in which the Queſtioniſt ungodlineſſe, is there diſcovered to their ſhame. 7. Reverend and ſuccinct Mr <hi>Sherlock</hi>'s anſwer to twen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty ſeven of the Quakers wild Queſtions,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mr Sherlock printed</hi> 1654.</note> and his lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned diſcourſe of the Spirit annexed, which might ſtay theſe erring wandring ſpirits, from their falſe preten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces to the ſpirit of Chriſt. 8 Read that profitable book,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>A brief relation printed</hi> 1653.</note> of that obſervant Author called A Briefe Relation of the Irreligion of the Northern Quakers, wherein their horrid principles and practiſes, doctrines and manners, are expoſed to the view of every intelligent Reader, and the Quakers <hi>Sauls</hi> errand to <hi>Damaſcus,</hi> in which are ſaid to be an hundred lies replied unto. 9.
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Antichriſt in man, printed</hi> 1655.</note> Witneſs that booke entituled Antichriſt in man, the Quakers Idoll, by Mr <hi>Joſhua Milner</hi> a ſervant of Chriſt in the Goſpell, in which is an anſwer and confutation of ſome of the Quakers dangerous and damnable doctrines. 10.
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mr Prins Qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kers unmasked, printed</hi> 1656.</note> witneſſe godly and learned Mr <hi>William Prinne</hi> Eſquire, detecting theſe Quakers to bee but the ſpawne of the Romiſh Frogs, Jeſuites, and Franciſcan Fryars, ſent from Rome to ſeduce poore ſoules in this Engliſh Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion;
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:62479:32" rendition="simple:additions"/>with his reply to <hi>John Audlands</hi> rayling paper, by which, and what I have proved in my Anſwer and Arguments upon the Queſtions before, which were Diſputed, any Chriſtians ſeeing eye, may ſee that <hi>James Nayler</hi> and his wandring fellow Quakers, are but poor pedlers for the Prieſts of Rome, and the Jeſuits ſervants, carrying up and downe the Nation, their packs of er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rours, and bags of paper-quaeries, invented and hatched in Antichriſts and the devils warehouſe, which they of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer at every door or place where they come, like brai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, bauſed, rotten wares, to deceive and couzen poor ſoules, and to diſturbe the peace and quiet of the Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, that this common enemy may more eaſily wheele us about to Rome, and Romiſh Tyranny, and ſo bring us to confuſion, from the higheſt to the loweſt; from which, God of his mercy protect us. And for Miniſters maintenance,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Gen.</hi> 14.20. <hi>Gen.</hi> 28.22. <hi>Lev.</hi> 27.30, 31. <hi>Numb.</hi> 18.21. <hi>Deut.</hi> 10.8, 9. <hi>Mal</hi> 3 8 9. <hi>Mat.</hi> 23 23. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 9 13.14. 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 5.17. <hi>Heb.</hi> 7.8. <hi>Printed for Mr Iohn Wright in the Old Bayly,</hi> 1646. <hi>Mr Deacons diſcovery, prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted</hi> 1656.</note> read Dr <hi>Carleton,</hi> Dr <hi>Tilleſley,</hi> Dr <hi>Slater,</hi> Sir <hi>Henry Spelman,</hi> Sir <hi>James Sempel,</hi> Mr <hi>William Prin</hi> Eſquire, my owne ſixt book (I have printed) called a light from Chriſt, leading unto Chriſt; and divers o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, who have ſufficiently proved Tythes not only lawfull, but due by divine Right to Chriſt, and the Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters of Chriſt in the Goſpell, and that the taking them away without due redemption, is that ſinne of ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>criledge. Laſt of all (for I let paſſe others) Read Mr <hi>John Deacon,</hi> a ſolid and ſharp Queſtioniſt, Replyant and Demandant, In his publike diſcovery of a ſecret deceit, or the man of ſin unmasked, and Satan transfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med into the reſemblance of an Angell of light, in that Sect or Society, commonly called Quakers, in which you have nineteen quaeries ſent to the Quakers Speak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, at the bull and mouth neer <hi>Aldersgate,</hi> and miſerably anſwered by <hi>James Nayler,</hi> whom he calleth juſtly, the grand fomentor of hereſie; and replyed unto by Mr <hi>Deacon,</hi> and fourteen more returned by <hi>Nayler,</hi> and fully anſwered by Mr <hi>Deacon;</hi> and foure and twenty more propoſed by Mr <hi>Deacon,</hi> which nor <hi>James Nay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler,</hi> nor any of his fellow Quakers (I believe) can truly
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:62479:32" rendition="simple:additions"/>and plainly anſwer, but they muſt denie the holy Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, or forſake their owne falſe erronious and hereti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call principles. And thus I have ſaid enough to direct <hi>James Nayler,</hi> and all his deceived, deluding Antichri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian phariſaicall company of Quakers, where they may finde Anſwers to their ſo much bragged of quae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries. It would be happy for them, if they could leave their errours, and enquire after the knowledge of Chriſt, that they may be taught by him <hi>Eph.</hi> 4.20, 21. as the truth is in Jeſus, which I deſire I may pray for. And now dear ſoules, if any of you that belong to Jeſus Chriſt, have been drawn away with the errour of theſe wicked perfect phariſees (as they are rightly called) return againe to your firſt Husband, Chriſt your Saviour, <hi>Hoſ.</hi> 2.7. you will finde it will be better with you ſo, then now it is, and fly the ſociety of theſe de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luding, equivocating, Antichriſtian Quakers, who ſpeak ſometimes of the Scriptures, but deny them to be the word of God, and make uſe of them in ſhew, but not in ſincerity and truth. Who pretend to a Chriſt within them, but deny the merits of Chriſts blood and righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſſe of Chriſt imputed to beleevers for Juſtifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and ſalvation. Some who proudly boaſt,
<note place="margin">George Fox Iames Nayler, &amp;c. proved before. Read their books, and where doe you read of asking forgiveneſſe of ſin for Chriſts ſake.</note> they are equall with God, and as holy, juſt and good, as God; that they are perfect, and without ſinne, and therefore ask no forgiveneſs of ſins at Gods hand, for Chriſts me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits ſake, caſting away both the Article of Faith, in which we profeſs we believe remiſſion of ſinnes; and that petition of the Lords prayer, in which our Saviour teacheth us to pray, Forgive us our treſpaſses, as we forgive them that treſpaſs againſt us. Yea they endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour to draw poore ſoules from Chriſts publike Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances, and to forſake the plain ſtraite way to Heaven, <hi>Mat.</hi> 7. like cheating thieves draw them into by waies,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mat.</hi> 7.14.</note> that they may-more ſecurely rob and ſpoil them of the rich treaſure of the Goſpell, and bleſsed way to glory.</p>
            <p>Seek then my friends to Chriſt, who is the wiſedome of the Father, <hi>Prov.</hi> 8.
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Col.</hi> 2.3.</note> for wiſedome and power to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>part
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:62479:33"/>from the tents of theſe wicked men,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Numb.</hi> 16.16.</note> and to turne againe unto the Lord, that ye periſh not in their Apoſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy from Chriſt. And for you my honoured pretious ſoules, and well beloved in the Lord Jeſus, who by ſtrength from Chriſt, have withſtood the temptations of theſe deluding Quakers, and are eſtabliſhed in the Faith of Chriſt, Watch ſtill, and beware ye be not drawn away with the errour of the wicked, and fall from your owne ſtedfaſtneſſe, and labour in the uſe of all good means; publike in the congregations of the ſaints, private in your families, and ſecret in your cloſets, by the power of Chriſt, and aſſiſtance of the Spirit of holineſs, <hi>John</hi> 15.5. <hi>Phil.</hi> 4.13. to grow in grace, and in the know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of our Lord and Saviour Jeſus Chriſt 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 3.17, 18. To whom with God the Father, and God the bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed Spirit, be glory both now and for ever.</p>
            <closer>Amen.</closer>
            <closer>
               <signed>Immanuel Bourne.</signed>
            </closer>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
